<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string-array name="Description">

        <item>A three-storey rectangular building with a risalite on the main facade. Covered hip roof with rectangular lucarnes. The main entrance is located in the risalite, the doorway is decorated with a portal. A balcony with a metal fence hangs over the entrance. The facades are plastered. Plastic restrained. The main facade is flanked by flat blades, divided by interstory rods. Rectangular window openings on the first floor without decoration, on the second – in profiled baseboards, on the third-are emphasized by window sill cornice belts. The southeastern facade of the end is deaf. The end north-west facade is cut through with rectangular window openings without decoration, on the second floor on the left side the window opening is located in a high arched niche. Adjacent to the facade is a (historical) (modern) (quenching / unsatisfactory / emergency) one-story household building. The rear facade on the right side is highlighted by a pair of flat blades that flank the doorway. The facade plane is divided according to the pattern with the main facade by interstory rods and rectangular window openings, on the second floor in profiled baseboards. A profiled cornice runs along the perimeter of the building. Covered hip roof with rectangular lucarnes. The main entrance is located in the risalite, the doorway is decorated with a portal. A balcony with a metal fence hangs over the entrance. The facades are plastered. Plastic restrained. The main facade is flanked by flat blades, divided by interstory rods. Rectangular window openings on the first floor without decoration, on the second – in profiled baseboards, on the third-are emphasized by window sill cornice belts. The southeastern facade of the end is deaf. The end north-west facade is cut through with rectangular window openings without decoration, on the second floor on the left side the window opening is located in a high arched niche. Adjacent to the facade is a (historical) (modern) (quenching / unsatisfactory / emergency) one-story household building. The rear facade on the right side is highlighted by a pair of flat blades that flank the doorway. The facade plane is divided according to the pattern with the main facade by interstory rods and rectangular window openings, on the second floor in profiled baseboards. A profiled cornice runs along the perimeter of the building.        </item>
        <item>A two-storey building with a basement is rectangular in plan, covered with a hip roof. The facades are plastered and painted, solved with restraint. (historical) (modern) (quenching/unsatisfactory/emergency).The main facade is rhythmically divided by rectangular window openings, on the first floor without decoration, on the second with accentuated straight sandricks decorated with stucco belts with cut ionics, palmettes and other elements. Roller shutters between the windows of the first and second floors are solved by shallow niches decorated with stucco frames with an ornamental belt. In the center of the facade there is a doorway of the main entrance, highlighted by a profiled skirting board with a large sandrik on decorative brackets in the shape of currencies. The finished facade has a cornice with dentils. The courtyard and end facades are solved simplistically, cut through with rectangular window openings without decor. On the courtyard facade, the window openings of the second floor are emphasized by cornice belts. There is a doorway in the center of the courtyard facade. There is an external metal staircase on the end northern facade.
        The end facades are completed with a cornice with dentils, a yard-profiled cornice. The internal layout of the building is corridor with a two-sided arrangement of rooms. The interior decoration is modern.</item>
        <item>Oval in terms of the sports core (football field, running tracks, sector for jumping and throwing) is surrounded by bleachers (more than 50 thousand people). seats). Most of them in the form of an amphitheater are located on a natural earthen slope. Halls for athletics, wrestling, boxing, office and administrative premises are located under the stands.. Through one large arch, above the entrances to the stands there are round bas-reliefs of sports themes, arched openings glazed. As a result of later reconstructions and modernizations, the original appearance of the stadium has been changed to a certain extent. The main entrance to the stadium from Kirov Street is represented by a three-span eight-column arcade and two side aisles.        </item>
        <item>A one-story building with a basement, built in the neoclassical style. It has an asymmetric composition. Above the western half of the house in 1979 – 1980, the second floor with a terrace was built on, the facades were plastered and painted, processed. The facade is pierced by two arched window openings, the extreme windows are decorated by analogy with the windows on the main facade. A doorway and two central window openings without decoration. On the facade side there was previously an open terrace. The southern corner of the building is indented from the front wall line. Here is the doorway of the entrance to the stairs. There is a canopy over the entrance. On the side northwest facade, a later built-up floor adjoins the tower, a stained glass window is made at the junction of the new wall with the tower from the southwest facade. The interior decoration has not been preserved.        </item>
        <item>A three-storey building with an overbuilt tower floor. The facade planes are solved laconically, represented by rectangular window and door openings. On the ground floor there is a rectangular doorway of the main entrance with a keystone. There are high arched window openings along the edges. On the second floor there is an open gallery with a balustrade fence. The facade is cut in the center by a rectangular window opening, arched niches are located along the edges. The corners of the tower are decorated with blades. The tower is divided into three low tiers by cornices. The facades of the lower tier are cut through with arched window and door openings, above which smaller arched window openings are placed in the second row. The main facade is decorated with the coat of arms of Minsk. Along the perimeter of the lower tier of the tower there is an open gallery with a balustrade (a fence made of curly posts with a fence). A clock is placed in the second tier of the tower. The third tier of the tower is represented by rounded window openings in the roof slope. The building is made in the classical style.        </item>
        <item>A four-storey U-shaped building with a basement. The main facade is oriented to Independence Avenue, the side ones are on Volodarsky and Sverdlov Streets. The main facade has a symmetrical axial composition. The central part with the entrance is made in the form of an arch building for the entire height of the building. Part of the facade above the arch is represented by a sculptural image of the coat of arms of the USSR. The side facades contain a cornice. The ground floor is cut through with rectangular window openings without decoration. The facade wall of the first floor is cut through with arched window openings, decorated with rectangular and round niches. The second tier (drum) contains narrow rectangular window openings, also a cornice. Later small additions were made to the courtyard facade. A neighboring building adjoins the end facade of the wing on Volodarsky Street. The main building has a corridor layout with a central front lobby on the ground floor. The main halls are highlighted by the characteristic decoration of that time. The main hall is covered by a thirty-meter dome, which rests on an internal colonnade. The columns are treated with artificial marble of green color. The walls of the lobby and the main hall are decorated with white marble, enriched with stucco decorative elements. The entrance to the hall is designed like a triumphal arch. The entrance opening is decorated with two columns. The hall is illuminated by large windows with arched completion, in which there are 15 stained glass compositions of 260x190 cm each, dedicated to the monuments of architecture of Belarus. Stained glass windows made of pieces of blue-blue, yellow, red, and orange glass. The compositions are bordered by a bluish-white geometric ornament. Enriches the interior of the hall granite floor geometric pattern. Located on the ground floor, the parcel hall and the telegraph hall are decorated more modestly.        </item>
        <item>The cathedral is a rectangular two-towered basilica. There is a basement under the temple. The main facade is divided into 3 tiers by cornices. In the center of the lower tier there is an arched doorway. On the first and second tiers, window openings are located in niches. In the second tier, the central niche has a curved outline. The third tier is formed by two side towers and a figured shield between them, filled with a modern image of the Mother of God. The side facades of the towers slightly protrude beyond the facades of the naves. An arched doorway is made in the lower tier of the side facade of the southwest tower. The narthex (an extension in front of the entrance to the temple) is also covered with cylindrical and cross vaults. A cornice runs along the perimeter of the walls. The openings of the entrances from the vestibule to the main part of the temple are lined with light gray marble. There are choirs above the entrance. In the altar part there is a three-tiered gilded iconostasis. The monumental main altar of the former church has been preserved behind the iconostasis. The columns are processed under artificial marble, the stucco details are covered with gilding. In a niche in the north-eastern wall of the cathedral there is a space with the relics of the righteous Sophia, Princess of Slutsk.        </item>
        <item>The building of the House of Officers has a complex plan form. The three-dimensional composition includes the main building facing Krasnoarmeyskaya St. and the side wings forming an inner courtyard. A cascade staircase with a fence and terraces leads to the courtyard from the back of the building from the local passage. The facades of the building are plastered. The main facade is executed in modernized classical forms according to a symmetrical scheme with a general asymmetric spatial composition of the building. The facade walls are cut through with rectangular window openings. The entrances are decorated with monumental wide passages. There are balconies above the entrances on the 4th floor. The window openings of the middle tier on the main and side facades are united by a common frame decorated with stucco elements with military attributes (shield, budenovka, five-pointed star). The upper row of rectangular small window openings is decorated with simple frames. The means of monumental and decorative art have been successfully used in the interior design. The architecture of the officers/\' house stands out for its strict, concise forms and successful functional and planning organization. The building is made in the style of post-constructivism.        </item>
        <item>A five-storey L-shaped building. The facades are plastered and painted, the main facades are decorated. The main emphasis is placed on the corner part, which is the shape of a tower divided into three tiers. The lower tier, corresponding to the three lower floors of the building, is cut through with high arched openings decorated with portals with stucco decoration. The second tier of the tower at a height of 4-5 floors is represented by an open terrace with a colonnade (columns of square section) and with a balustrade fence. The upper tier is one-story. On the 4th floor, balconies on concrete consoles and with balustrade fences are arranged in a certain sequence. The openings of the balconies are represented by stucco elements in arched frames. Above the balconies on the fifth floor there are wide window openings.        </item>
        <item>A two-story rectangular elongated building, completed in the center with a one-story superstructure of the dispatch service. The facades are plastered. The superstructure is covered with a gable roof. The main facade is highlighted by a wide six-column portico on the sides with arched openings. On the opposite facade, the exit to the runway is also solved by a portico (the protruding part of the building). The end facades are decorated with four-column porticos. The staircase and gallery have balustrades (a fence made of curly columns with railings) and parapets. The lobby interiors are decorated with pilasters, columns and various stucco elements. The rest of the premises (waiting rooms, restaurant, office space) are solved more modestly.        </item>
        <item>A four-story rectangular building. The composition is based on the type of an ancient Roman temple. The main facade facing the square is represented by a 12-column canopy (passage). In the archway there is a central multi-figure sculptural composition dedicated to the theme of labor and peace. In the second tier, stucco elements like antique vases are a continuation of the columns. In the center of the facade there are three high arched openings-entrances in frames. Above the arched openings in the second tier, the facade wall is cut through by three high rectangular window openings in the baseboards. On the edges of the main facade on the ground floor there are arched window openings, above rectangular. The interiors of the main rooms (halls, couloirs, foyers) are richly decorated with stucco elements in the style characteristic of that period, the columns are treated with artificial marble, the walls are white marble and decorative colored plaster.        </item>
        <item>The three-storey rectangular building is covered with a hip (four-pitched) roof. The facades are plastered. In the center of the main facade on the ground floor there is a doorway decorated with a simple frame. The doorway consists of narrow window openings. A wide cornice runs along the perimeter of the building. On the ground floor there are rectangular window openings without decoration. A stone fence adjoins the building from the street side. The building is made in the classical style.        </item>

        <item>The monument is installed on the main alley of the park. On a horizontal pedestal – a granite block – there is a full-length bronze figure of the poet, as if the dome ascended the hill and froze, fascinated by the surroundings. Pesnyar, in a coat draped over his shoulders, leans on a Gnarled staff with his right hand, the left is placed on his chest. The wind twisted the collar of the coat and slightly deflected the floor. In the whole figure of the poet, in the expression of the face, romantic sublimity, aspiration to the future, nobility and human charm are emphasized. A spring breaks through the stones at the poet\'s feet, and a fabulous fern flower has spread its bronze leaves next to her. Description of the distinctive spiritual, artistic and (or) documentary merits of the material historical and cultural value, as well as elements, structures, details subject to mandatory preservation: The monument was erected to the People\'s writer of Belarus Yanka Kupala. Without exaggeration, his work can be called a song about Belarus. Many monuments are dedicated to the Great Belarusian singer, but this one is the most majestic. The spiritualized figure of the poet-fighter, thinker embodies the best human traits-humanism, high morality. The convincing vitality of the image of Yanka Kupala is achieved both by the thoughtfulness of the composition and by the plastic structure. A horizontally sprawled pedestal of an asymmetrical shape from the depths of untreated granite seems to connect it with the earth. The poetic images of the spring and the popart-flowers are very harmonious. The authors of the monument: People\'s Artists of Belarus A. Anikeychik and L. Gumilevsky, Honored Artist of Belarus A. Zaspitsky, Honored Architects of Belarus Yu. Gradov and L. Levin. The creative team for the monument to Yanka Kupala received the State Prize of the BSSR.        </item>
        <item>"The monument is oriented towards ave. Independence. It is a spatial sculptural composition, the dominant of which is the bronze figure of the national poet. On both sides of it there are sculptural groups of the heroes of his works, the Quagmire, and Simon the musician,. The poet is shown in adulthood. Lost in thought, he sits on a Large boulder-Stone. There is a wise peace and reflection in his whole figure. Vital concreteness, portrait similarity are the distinctive features of the sculpture. Large forms enhance the monumentality of the image. To the right of the main sculpture is a group: grandfather Talash and his son Panas. They seem to have descended from the pages, quagmires, - they are on patrol, peering warily into the distance. Lyrical
        images of the second sculptural group-Simon-music and the peasant girl Anna, with her head propped on her hands, listens to the blind musician with fascination. All the elements of the sculptural composition are arranged symmetrically, in harmonic balance and organically part of the overall ensemble of the square. Lawns of different shapes, groups of birches, weeping willow, small fountains that resemble ears of corn in shape and symbolize the living force of the native land, give the monument an emotional coloring. "        </item>
        <item>The monument was erected in the park near the Bolshoi Theater of Belarus. It is oriented to M. Bogdanovich Street, to the place where the house in which the poet was born stood. The sculpture is mounted on a low stepped pedestal made of red granite. The poet is shown in full height with his arms crossed on his chest, with a bouquet of cornflowers in his right hand. The foreshortening of the figure, the thoughtful gaze directed into the distance reflects filial love for the native Belarusian land. There is a slight, barely noticeable smile on his face, mixed with sadness. In the bronze figure, in the poet\'s pose, the romance of youth, strength of spirit, restrained impulse are emphasized. In his right hand, Bogdanovich holds a bouquet of Cornflowers dear to his heart - a symbol of the Motherland.A commemorative inscription is made on the edge of the pedestal, underlined with an ornamental ribbon. Description of the distinctive spiritual, artistic and (or) documentary merits of material historical and cultural value, as well as elements, structures, details subject to mandatory preservation: The monument is dedicated to Maxim Bogdanovich-the famous Belarusian poet, publicist, translator, public figure. In the bronze figure, youth, romantic thoughtfulness, and love for the native land are conveyed without too much pathos. The author of the monument is the famous Belarusian sculptor, Honored Artist of Belarus S. Vakar. His co-authors are architect Yu. Kazakov and Honored Architect of Belarus L. Moskalevich.</item>
        <item>The grave of Yanka Kupala is located in the northern part of the Military Cemetery. The tombstone is solved in a romantic way. It is a vertical wall of granite blocks, on the background of which there is a sculptural figure of Ya. Kupala. The poet is sitting on a stone with his right hand lowered, barefoot, which emphasizes his organic connection with his native land. He is wearing a loose shirt with an open collar, and a coat is thrown over his left shoulder. The calm, thoughtful face is turned in profile. Concentration, poetic impulse is reflected on the face. The interpretation of the image is soft, generalized, the portrait features are worked out in detail. There is a plaque with a commemorative inscription on the stele. Description of the distinctive spiritual, artistic and (or) documentary merits of the material historical and cultural value, as well as elements, structures, details subject to mandatory preservation: The tombstone monument is an example of monumental art made by famous Belarusian sculptors A. Anikeychik, A. Zaspitsky and architect M. Myznikov. It is installed on the grave of the national poet of Belarus.        </item>
        <item>The grave of Yakub Kolas is located on a small terrace in the northern part of the cemetery. The terrace is fixed with retaining walls. The monument on the grave is a vertically elongated block with uneven edges. In its upper part there is a sculptural portrait of the national poet, solved in generalized plastic. A peculiar effect is achieved with the help of various stone processing. The matte light gray surface of the sculptural forms stands out in contrast against the background of darker-toned rough chips. The lower part of the block with the facsimile signature of Yakub Kolas has a smooth surface. The compositional combination of architectural and sculptural forms, the choice of proportions, the accuracy of plastic characteristics give the monument a monumental expressiveness. Description of the distinctive spiritual, artistic and (or) documentary merits of the material historical and cultural value, as well as elements, structures, details subject to mandatory preservation: The tombstone monument is a sample of monumental art made by Belarusian sculptors V. Ananko and M. Yakovenko, architect M. Myznikov. It is installed on the grave of the national poet of Belarus.        </item>
        <item>The monument is designed in the form of a majestic obelisk lined with gray granite, topped with an image of the Order, Victory, (bronze with gilding, glass, total height about 38 m). The sides of the obelisk are rhythmically dissected by narrow and completed with wide stripes resembling the Belarusian ornament. 4 sides of the pedestal are decorated with bronze high reliefs: ,May 9, 1945,, ,The Soviet Army during the Great Patriotic War,, ,Glory to the fallen heroes,, ,partisans of Belarus,. By successive alternation of reliefs, laconic plastic means, the culminating moments of the struggle of the Soviet people against the Nazi invaders, the bitterness of losses, the joy of victory are emotionally conveyed. Multi-figure compositions are made in a realistic manner, with detailed elaboration of relief images. The obelisk is placed on a faceted stylobate expanded at the bottom, which depicts a bronze sword entwined with a Laurel branch. The whole composition is located on a wide octagonal stepped podium, the four sides of which are cut with cubic stylobates (black labradorite) with four bronze laurel wreaths on them. Description of the distinctive spiritual, artistic and (or) documentary merits of material historical and cultural value, as well as elements, structures, details subject to mandatory preservation: The Victory Monument was erected in honor of the victory of the Soviet people over Nazi Germany. It is the compositional dominant of the ensemble of Victory Square. It was erected according to the project of the People \'s Architects of the USSR . Zaborsky and V. Korol with the participation of the People \'s Artist of the BSSR and the USSR Z. Azgur, folk artists of the BSSR A. Bembel, A. Glebov and S. Selikhanov. The architectural and sculptural composition of the monument is subject to mandatory preservation: an obelisk completed with the Order of Victory, the decoration of the obelisk faces, bronze high reliefs on a pedestal, a stylobate depicting a bronze sword, a stepped podium, four stylobates with bronze wreaths.        </item>

        <item>Monumental complex three-dimensional composition of the building. The three-dimensional composition is created according to the principle of tiers. The walls are rhythmically made with high rectangular window openings and shoulder blades. The visual part consists of 3 cylindrical volumes of different diameters and heights placed on top of each other, highlighted by 7 square entrance porticos. The columns of the porticos are treated with shallow Rustication.The developed stage box and auxiliary rooms are attached in the form of a high rectangular in plan and lower cubic volumes protruding on the sides. The main facade is decorated with thematic sculptural compositions. The backstage part is rectangular in plan with volumes at the corners.The auditorium is made according to the traditional tiered scheme in the stalls and upper shallow tiers (mezzanine, balcony). Wardrobes, foyers and couloirs are spacious and bright. In their design, as well as in the decoration of the auditorium, sculpture, decorative vases, artistic stucco details, coffered ceilings, decorative plaster, gilding, drapery, marble cladding, granite and parquet floors, etc. are used. Especially the richly decorated portal of the stage        </item>
        <item>The two-storey building with a basement is rectangular in plan with a symmetrical three-dimensional composition. The main facade is highlighted by a powerful six-column portico with a massive triangular pediment and Corinthian order columns, at the end of the pediment a cornice with a molded frieze is developed. On the facade, the columns of the portico correspond to fluted pilasters with the same capitals, a high multi-stage porch leads to the main entrance. The central part of the facade with doorways is slightly recessed) rectangular doorways are decorated with profiled platbands with sandricks on decorative brackets, enriched with stucco garlands, above there is a triple arched window opening framed with columns, on the sides of the facade there is one narrow arched window emphasized by a draft. The main facade is flanked by flat blades, the main volume of the building on the main facade is also completed with a triangular pediment surrounded by a cornice. The front wall under the pediment is cut through by a wide semicircular window opening. The side facades, which are directly adjacent to the main facade and belong to the historical building, are plastered with masonry. The rest of the side facades of the main volume are draped with two-tiered pilasters, on the ground floor the facades are cut with rectangular openings horizontally, the facades are separated by a draft, completed with a profiled cornice, a later volume is attached to the back of the building, its facades are solved smoothly, cut with rectangular window openings without decor. The interior space is also decided symmetrically, the former central nave converted into an auditorium, side ((in the foyer) in the interior decoration used order plastic, molded frieze belts, cornices, pilasters with capitals of stylized Corinthian and Ionic orders, profiled baseboards, molded rosettes, garlands, etc. The theater building is connected by a passage to the building where the small stage is located. The building is two-storeyed with a complex three-dimensional composition. The Facades Are Plastered. the main and rear facades in the center are highlighted with faceted risalites\' on the rear facade there is a side risalite, on the main facade the main emphasis is placed on the angular rounded part, divided on the first and second floors by rectangular window openings decorated with niches, on the east side there is a lower vestibule, on top of which there is an open terrace with a metal fence. The entrance is decorated with a two-column portico, covered with a massive arch. The central part of the facade, except for the risalite, is finally extended by a pediment. On the left side of the risalit on the main facade there is a high arched niche, rectangular window openings are emphasized by window sill cornice belts, on the main facade on the first floor of the risalit is decorated with niches.        </item>
        <item>The main facade of the building, oriented to the avenue, is decorated with a colonnade of the Corinthian order. The walls around the perimeter are robbed by flat pilasters, on the main facade the pilasters also have capitals of the Corinthian order. The doorways of the main entrance are decorated with profiled portals with straight sandricks. Rectangular window openings without decoration. The facades are completed with a profiled cornice with a belt of crackers.        </item>
        <item>The three-storey rectangular building is covered with a gable roof, a 5-storey wing has been completed to the end of the building, the facades are solved strictly and concisely, the main facade is decorated with a portico with 1 fluted pillar, a triangular pediment, the slopes of the pediment and the portico facades are completed with a cornice with dentils and a narrow belt of stucco frieze. The side facades of the portico are decorated with arched openings. the main entrances are solved with the same high arched openings in simple frames) semicircular risalites of the foyer stairs stand out on the side facades. The facades of the risalites have a tiered structure. The lower tier is interpreted as a high plinth, the second tier is divided by high rectangular window openings and horizontally rusticated pilasters. Between the second and third tiers there is a cornice with a thin molded frieze, the third tier is smaller in volume, completed with a profiled cornice with a molded frieze) the risalites are accentuated by triangular pediments on the main volume, the slopes of the pediment are completed with a cornice with a molded thin frieze. The facades of the building are decorated with plaster for block masonry and completed with a powerful cornice, roller shutters between the windows of the side facades are marked with wide blades with floral ornamental belts at the end. the windows of the first and second floors are vertically united by profiled frames with window sills, the windows of the third floor are emphasized by a cornice and a stucco thin frieze. The concert hall is designed in the form of an amphitheater. The two-light foyer with a mezzanine gallery has a colonnade.        </item>

        <item>The church is a brick cross-domed three-day one-apse four-stop memorial church. In the center of the symmetrical volumetrically spacious composition rises a massive dome on an octagonal light drum, completed with a bow-shaped crown. A smaller decorative dome is placed on the roof of the altar apse. The dominant feature of the composition is a high 2—tier belfry with a hipped roof, placed above the narthex. The rich plasticity of the facades is given by multiple architectural belts, complex decorative arches over window and door openings, rosettes, ornamental frieze, intricately profiled cornice, columns. Decorative elements are highlighted in white. The altar part is separated from the main room, with semicircular stumps above it on the Estuary. The central nave opens into side arched openings. In the vestibule at the entrance to the central nave there are memorial plaques with the names of 118 Belarusian soldiers of the 30th Artillery Brigade and the 119th Kolomna Regiment who died at Plevna during the Russo—Turkish War of 1877-78. The church is a monument of pseudo—Russian style architecture.        </item>
        <item>The building has a complex spatial composition. The plan is close to the letter P. The facades are plastered, richly decorated with order plastic. The five-storey volume on the side of the main facade is highlighted by six-storey and seven-storey risalites. A wide central seven-storey risalit of symmetrical composition. In the center of it there is a high (to the height of two floors) arched niche in a profiled frame. In the niche there is a doorway decorated with a portal with a straight sandrik on decorative brackets. Between the doorway and the window wall in the niche is decorated with a stucco floral pattern in combination with Soviet symbols. The wall of the first floor is treated with large Rustication, like masonry, cut with window openings of different widths. The plane of the facade wall on the 2nd-3rd floors is rusticated, but not so large rusticated. It is divided by rectangular window openings without decoration, on the 3rd and 4th floors there are small balconies with metal fences. The facade wall of the 5th-7th floors is grouped with capellated pilasters with stylized Corinthian capitals. On the 5th floor, small balconies with balustrade railings, decorated with rectangular platbands with straight sandricks, and wider balconies, decorated with platbands with a semicircular sandric with a keystone and a shell in the tympanum, rhythmically alternate. Arched passages are located on both sides of the central risalite at the junction with the side wings. The side risalits are six-storeyed and narrow (three openings wide). In the center there are deep rectangular outlines of niches with doorways, decorated with profiled portals with straight sandricks. The facade plane of the risalites from below to half of the third floor is treated with large rusticated masonry, cut through with rectangular window openings without decor. Between the 3rd and 4th floors, the facades of the risalites are separated by an ornamented frieze. The window openings on the 4th floor are decorated with elaborate stucco trim elements. The sheet shutters on the 4th-5th floors are decorated with an intricate floral and geometric stucco pattern. On the 5th floor, the window openings are in simple baseboards, the piers are filled with stucco images of VASES. The risalites are completed with a multi-layered cornice. The corner part of the building at the intersection of ave . Independence and Kozlov St. are rounded. In the center there is an arched niche to the height of the two lower floors, decorated with decorative framing. In the niche there is a doorway decorated with a portal with a sandrik, the wall between the portal and the window is decorated with stucco elements. Window openings on the ground floor are decorated with simple platbands with window sill cornice belts on brackets and sandricks on brackets. The upper 4th and 5th floors are accentuated by a wide loggia with a balustrade fence and plundered by 6 columns of the stylized Corinthian order. The main facade of the five-storey part of the building between the central and side risalit on the right side, as well as the facade of the wing on Kozlov Street are solved more restrainedly. Their planes are separated by an ornamental floral pattern traction between the 3rd and 4th floors. The walls of the 1st-3rd floors are treated with Rust. On the ground floor, the main facade from the avenue side is highlighted by two arched profiled wide frames of doorways, the facade from Kozlov Street has a similar frame, but rectangular in outline. On the 4th floor, a certain rhythm of facades is created by arched folding baseboards of the openings of balcony doors, enriched with stucco details, garlands of oak, wrapped with ribbons. The facades of the pros are completed with an obvious cornice. The main facade of the part of the building between the central risalit and the side risalit on the left side has a similar architectural solution. The facade of the side left wing of the building in the corner part is highlighted by a shallow risalite.        </item>

        <item>"The territory of the former death camp " Trostenets " is located in the area of pr . Partizansky, Selitsky St. and UR. Blagoveshchyna includes several zones: the reception point for prisoners, the ""road of death"", the site of the camp proper, where the camp infrastructure facilities were located, the place of execution. The site of the prisoners\' reception point (former Road construction site no. 2) located southwest of ave. Partizansky and the other two sides are conditionally limited by the strip of the Mikhanovichi-Stepyanka railway and the segment of Rotmistrova St.. The plot is planted with young trees. The ""Road of Death"" is a poplar alley along which prisoners moved. Runs in a south-easterly direction from ave. Partisan (approximately from the Bolshoy Trostenets public transport stop) to the place where the shed was located, in which 6.5 thousand prisoners were burned. It has been preserved in fragments. The territory of the camp proper is located to the west of the village of Maly Trostenets, between Selitsky Street and the reservoir. Commemorative signs have been installed on this territory at the site of the cremation furnace and the place of the outbuildings in which the fascists burned 6.5 thousand prisoners. Outside the territory of the former death camp on the northeast side of the ave. Partizansky is a monument to the victims of fascism, installed in 1963. The obelisk monument is placed on a stylobate. The sides of the pedestal are decorated with wreaths and a commemorative plaque. The Eternal Flame is located on the axis of the monument. In 2004, the remains of Soviet Army soldiers who died in the Great Patriotic War and were buried in a mass grave along the Mogilev Highway (10 km) were reburied to the monument."        </item>
        <item>"The memorial complex is located at the intersection of Timiryazev and Narochanskaya Streets, in Leska. The plot of the stalag-352 cemetery is quadrangular in plan with a slight break. Elongated along the southwest-northeast axis. A 5 m wide staircase leads to the memorial from Timiryazev Street . from the entrance, paths lead to the monument. The monument is a Stele made under a ragged stone. On the main facade of the wall there is a commemorative inscription: ""contemporaries and descendants, bow your heads. Those who did not kneel before the enemy sleep here forever "" and the date 1941-1945. On top is a wreath with a star, under it is a crossed weapon. Behind the monument there is a burial plot with tombstones. The main compositional axis is the central alley, along which the burials are located. There are cross paths between the rows of mass graves. The central alley approaches the site in the northern part of the complex, on which a truncated obelisk is located in the center. It contained a ""Book of Memory"" with a list of over 9,000 names of prisoners identified."        </item>
        <item>"The monument was created on the site of the pit where on March 2, 1942, the Nazis shot prisoners of the Minsk ghetto, one of the largest in Europe. The main element of the monument is the bronze sculpture composition ""the last way"". It is located along the stairs leading in it to the center of the memorial. It is a group of doomed martyrs descending to the bottom of the pit. 27 figures, like faceless and silent shadows, humbly descend to meet death. At the bottom of the pit is an obelisk made of black granite, erected in 1947. On it, in Russian and Yiddish, memorable words are written: ""Bright memory for bright times to five thousand Jews who died at the hands of fierce enemies of Man – fascist-German villains. 2.03.1942"". The bottom of the pit is lined with black paving stones. The memorial includes an alley of the ""Righteous of the World"" with trees planted in honor of the citizens of Belarus who saved Jewish families during the war, a decorative element – a minor, on which words of gratitude to all those with whose help the monument was created. Description of the distinctive spiritual, artistic and (or) documentary merits of the material historical and cultural value, as well as elements, structures, details subject to mandatory preservation:The monument was erected in memory of the victims of Hitler\'s genocide -the peaceful Jewish population. The idea of the monument is the eternal memory of the Holocaust. The authors of the monument are the famous sculptor, laureate of the State Prize of the Republic of Belarus A. Finsky, Israeli sculptor E. Polak and Honored Architect of the Republic of Belarus, laureate of the Lenin Prize and the Lenin Komsomol Prize, twice laureate of the State Prize of the Republic of Belarus"        </item>
        <item>The burial place of prisoners of war and civilians of the concentration camp ""Drozdy"" is located in a field on the west side of the Dolgovsky tract and to the east of Lenin Street. Nevavilonskaya, near the water pump station, poultry farm and garage complex. As it was established as a result of the search work carried out by the 52nd separate specialized search battalion of the Department for Perpetuating the Memory of Defenders of the Fatherland and Victims of Wars, the remains of concentration camp prisoners are in a trench pit 375 m long, 2.5 m wide, 2.5 m deep. There is a memorial stone on this place, on which the words are carved: ""Here in July 1941, the Nazi occupiers shot prisoners of war of the concentration camp ""Drozdy"", civilians of Minsk and surrounding villages (about 10 thousand people). Posterity remembers you."" A small area near the monument stone is surrounded on three sides by a symbolic fence. The area in front of the stone is tiled and lined with birches on both sides, a bench is placed on it from the side. The main part of the burial is a plot of land overgrown with vegetation. The boundaries of the burial are marked with temporary wooden poles with the inscription ""Mass grave"".        </item>
        <item>In memory of 30,000 executed and buried in mass graves in the area of the former d . Uruchye and the cornice tract is a swamp of prisoners of war and civilians. A monument has been erected. The monument is located on the 9th km of the Moscow highway, opposite the main entrance to the territory of the Military Academy of the Republic of Belarus.The monument is an obelisk placed on a faceted stylobate lined with red granite. On the main facade of the obelisk from below in a granite frame there is a memorial plaque with a commemorative inscription, above it the date-1941-1945 and a laurel wreath, at the top - a five-pointed star. On both sides of the obelisk on the wall there are concrete images of flags at half-mast. A staircase leads to the obelisk. To the left of the stairs in the lower tier of the stylobate are 33 established names of soldiers and partisans buried in a mass grave. In front of the monument there is a landscaped area laid out with paving slabs. Benches are installed on it and two lawns with Christmas trees grow on the edges of the site with a border. A wide staircase leading to the site in front of the monument is flanked by two flower beds lined with red granite.        </item>
        <item>The cemetery occupies a block bounded by Kozlov Street, Berestyanka, Krasnozdnaya, Mikhailova. The territory of the cemetery is surrounded by a metal fence on stone pillars. The main entrance is located on the side of Kozlov Street. They are solved by three-span stone gates, from which the main alley begins. Leads to the Church of Alexander Nevsky. To the west of the gate there is an entrance and an alley to the site of military graves occupying the north-western part of the cemetery. Grave graves of Soviet soldiers, partisans, underground workers who died in the Great Patriotic War, graves of Heroes of the Soviet Union are located here. The earliest burials in the cemetery are the graves of servicemen who died in the Minsk military hospital. In Soviet times it became a city cemetery, many party and state figures, famous scientists, representatives of creative professions, etc. are buried here. In 1948, a monument was erected on the grave of M. D. Mickiewicz, the wife of J. Kolas. The monument is designed in the classical traditions of tombstones: the truncated obelisk is crowned with an urn, from which drapery and garlands of flowers entwined with a ribbon fall. On the front plane of the obelisk is a medallion with a relief portrait image of the deceased (sculptor Z. Azgur) framed by a flower garland and a rose branch. The area around the grave is bounded by a low granite fence. The difference in terrain is fixed by retaining walls made of rubble stone (architect G. Zaborsky). In 1970, a monument was erected on the grave of Ya. Kolas (sculptor. V. Ananka, M. Yakovenko, architect. M. Myznikov, granite, height 4 m). The monument is a vertically elongated block with uneven edges. In the upper part of it there is a sculptural portrait of the writer, solved in generalized plastic. a peculiar effect is achieved with the help of various stone processing. The matte light gray surface of the sculptural forms stands out in contrast against the background of darker rough chips by a ton. The lower part of the block with the facsimile signature of Y. Kolas has a smooth surface. The compositional combination of architectural and sculptural forms, the choice of proportions, the accuracy of plastic characteristics give the monument a monumental expressiveness.In 1971, a monument was erected on the grave of Ya. Kupala (sculptures by A. Anikeychik, A. Zaspitsky, architect M. Myznikov; granite, bronze; high. Walls 4.1 m, figures 3 m). Against the background of a vertical wall of granite blocks is a sculptural figure of Ya. Kupala. The poet is shown sitting with his back against the wall, his hands are lowered, concentration in his face, a poetic impulse. The interpretation is soft, generalized, the portrait features are worked out in detail.        </item>
        <item>The territory of the former Fraternal cemetery is surrounded on three sides (from the streets) by a metal openwork fence on a low retaining wall. Between the spans of the fence are faceted pillars lined with dark gray granite and topped with urns. On the fourth side (from the residential building), the territory is separated by low metal columns, between which there is a chain. The entrances from Chervyakova Street and Starovilensky Tract, decorated with two pylons, are located on one axis. The third entrance is located on the side of V. Khoruzhey Street. Highlighted by sculptures of angels mounted on pylons. The territory is divided by three perpendicular oils that lead from the entrance gate to the center. In the center there is a stone chapel in neoclassical forms, completed with a dome. The corners of the chapel are decorated with semi-columns supporting entablatures and triangular pediments. A mosaic icon ""The Sign of the Virgin"" is placed on the wall of the chapel. Above is the image ""Saved by Man-made"". The dome is also decorated with a mosaic pattern. There is a circular platform in front of the chapel. On four sides there are granite slabs with the names of the buried. Lanterns complement the memorial complex of the original shape.        </item>

        <item>The territory of the park is limited by ave. Independence, Ya. Kupala str., Svisloch river. The park is of mixed type, the layout combines regular and landscape features: the geometric grid oil contrasts with the colorful bend of the river. In the composition of the park, the main role is played by a diagonal alley starting from the main entrance from ave. Independence, and on which there is a monument to Ya. Kupala. The entrance is flanked by lighting columns. In the center of the park there is a parade ground, facing the bank of the Svisloch River. It is finished with an architecturally designed descent to the water with wide staircases and massive concrete balls. A grid of freely laid paths diverges from the main alleys. The artistic integrity of the park is given by condensed plantings along the perimeter, along alleys and stalls. The main alleys in certain areas are planted with a single tree species, mainly small-leaved lime. Among the plantings, local breeds predominate: linden, holly maple, common oak, common ash, warty birch, white acacia, common mountain ash, dogwood, snowfall, etc. Among the exotics are plum spruce, Siberian fir, Western thuja, horse chestnut, Manchurian walnut, blue maple, Tatar maple.        </item>
        <item>The caretaker\'s house is a stone one-story rectangular small building in plan. Covered gable roof. The vestibule attached to the front facade is covered with a lean-to roof. The facades are danced, the plastic is simplified. Rectangular window openings are decorated with wedged lintels, window sill cornice belts. The pediments were decorated with wooden carved elements.        </item>
        <item>The estate complex has been preserved relatively holistically: residential and office buildings, industrial buildings, a park, a chapel. The center of the composition of the manor complex is the manor house-a one-two-storey building on a high basement, rectangular in plan, with an asymmetric three-dimensional composition. The one-story wooden part is covered with a gable roof, the two–story brick part is covered with a high four-pitched roof, the risalites are covered with gable roofs. The facades are plastered, the basement is lined with stone. The central entrance is highlighted by the original portico. Decorated with carvings, 10 thin wooden columns placed on a high porch support a complex wooden pediment-visor. Open porches on the south-eastern and north-eastern facades are decorated like a portico. Rectangular window openings of the ground floor are decorated with plaster frames. The rectangular windows of the first and second floors of the stone volume are decorated with carved wooden platbands with sandricks. Pediments and cornices are decorated with carved decorative elements. According to the act of investigation in 1987 the interior has preserved 16 stoves and one fireplace, moldings (sockets, cornices). Three stoves are lined with brown relief tiles, one stove with polychrome tiles, the others with white tiles. The fireplace is lined with green relief tiles.        </item>
        <item>A landscape-type park with regular elements. The historically developed planning composition of the old garden has mostly been preserved. The basis of the layout consists of 3 straight alleys intersected in different directions by paths and trails. The landscape composition of the park is enriched by the Svisloch riverbed, a diversion channel with decorative reservoirs. The banks of the river are landscaped, one of the main walking routes runs along the embankment. The park is richly saturated with architecture of small forms: pavilions, gazebos, pedestrian bridges, modern lighting fixtures, etc. There are more than 60 species of trees and shrubs in the park, mainly of local breeds: birch, pine, spruce, rowan, weeping willow. There are also rare plants: cedar pine, California fir, European larch, field maple and silver. Decorative groups of old lime trees and maples, Weimut pine trees have been preserved. Deep landscape curtains have been created in the park, complemented by plantings of shrubs, flower beds. The administrative building is one-story L-shaped in plan, covered with a hip roof. The facades are faced with red brick, partially plastered and painted. The main facade is draped with pilasters, pierced with arched window openings. The main entrance is decorated with an open vestibule under a gable roof. The front and courtyard facade is divided by arched window openings with wedged lintels, there is no decor. A multilayer cornice runs along the perimeter under the roof. The side wing of the building is completed. The territory of the park is surrounded by a fence: a metal lattice between stone pillars decorated with balls.        </item>
    </string-array>
</resources>