<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string-array name="History">

        <item> Building No. 17a is located in the Trinity suburb, which is an integral part of the historical center of Minsk. The Registry Office building was erected as a result of a comprehensive reconstruction of the historical quarter carried out in the 1980s. The analysis of historical plans showed that the building No. 17a is located on the square, which according to the administrative division of Minsk in the late 19th-early 20th century had an ordinal No. 2 and belonged to the block No. 47. the then owner of the square was Meyer Abramov Zuckerman. He inherited the square with the stone house in 1855 . The last owner of the square was Aizik Meerov Zuckerman. The main building of M. Zuckerman\'s household until recently had No. 17, now it is combined with houses No. 13 and 15 under one No. 13. On the plans of Minsk in the first third of the 19th century, a stone rectangular house is indicated on the site of building No. 17. In the courtyard, approximately on the site of the modern building No. 17a, a wooden wing is marked, outbuildings adjoined its end facade. The following information about the development of Zuckerman Square dates back to the second half of the 19th century . After the fire in 1877 the landlord submitted to the city council a petition and a project for the overhaul of a three-storey residential building standing along the street line. In addition, according to the project, it was planned to build a bench along the street and two wooden outbuildings in the courtyard. The outbuildings were designed in the western part of the square, on the site of the modern house No. 17a. At the beginning of the 20th century. on the site of the wooden outbuildings designed in 1877, a stone one-storey residential building and a stone stable were already located next to it. The stone house was square in plan, measuring 12x12x7 arsh. The stable was the same size. So, on the site of the house under modern No. 17a at the beginning of the 20th century there was a stone one-storey residential building and in one connection with it a stone stable. The construction situation on the former site of the Zuckermans persisted in the post-war period. The detailed plan of Minsk in 1948 shows that the aforementioned residential building and stable were preserved, but were combined into one single-storey residential building. In 1982-1987, the building of the Registry office of the Central District was built on the site of a residential building.</item>
        <item>The building is located in the historical center of Minsk, in the so-called Rakovsky suburb. Forms the building of Vitebsk Street. The block in which building No. 21 is located was formed on the western outskirts of the Rakovsky suburb. The boundaries of the block were the streets: Novo-Romanovskaya, Yurievo-Zavalnaya, Rakovskaya, Nemiga-Rakovskaya (or Voskresenskaya Street), Nemigsky Lane. Novo-Romanovskaya and Yurieva-Zavalnaya streets were formed in the first half of the 19th century on the site of the demolished city rampart. The planning structure of the quarter was preserved until the middle of the 20th century . From the above-mentioned streets, there are now Novoromanovskaya (modern Romanovskaya Sloboda Street), Rakovskaya Street. Nemiga-Rakovskaya Street (or lane) and a small segment of the lane. Nemigsky correspond to the modern Vitebsk street. Yurieva-Zavalnaya Street in Soviet times was renamed Khlebnaya Street, preserved on the northern segment as a dead-end passage along the fence of bakery No. 1.according to archival documents, the site at the junction of Nemiga- Nemigorakovskaya Street. After the revolution, the buildings were municipalized.. During the Great Patriotic War, the stone building that stood along the street line was damaged. His box was dismantled, and the vacated area of 0.1 hectares was allocated by the decision of the Minsk City Executive Committee No. 288 dated 04/28/1951 for the construction of workshops of the Mining and Industrial Complex of the Ministry of Local Industry. The decision states that the site is allocated for the construction of a stone two-storey industrial premises with the prospect of building it up to 4 floors and preserving the passage to the BSU dormitory (house No. 21a). The architectural and planning task for the design of a 2-storey building was signed by the head of the Department for Architecture Affairs of Minsk on 23.06.1951. it prescribed that the production building should be placed according to the red lines issued. The design work was carried out in 1951-52 in the architectural and planning workshop under the office of the Chief Architect of Minsk in several stages. The author of the project is architect T. A. Komanin. Tamara Antonovna Komanina graduated from the Moscow Architectural Institute in 1950. Since 1964, she has been a member of the Union of Architects of the USSR. At the beginning, in accordance with the planned and architectural planning task, a project task was developed. The building of the workshops was designed to be two-storeyed with a basement, placed along the red line of Nemigsky Lane. It was planned to place a sewing, shoe and repair workshop for small metal products for household purposes, administrative premises. On 12.10.1951, the project assignment was reviewed and approved by the Architectural Council of the Department of Architecture of Minsk (Protocol No. 37). When developing the technical project, it was necessary to take into account the remark concerning the internal layout-to open the lobby and reception area to give them a more ceremonial character. The project assignment was also agreed with some comments by the Fire Department of the Ministry of Internal Affairs of the BSSR and the State Sanitary Inspection of Minsk. According to the drawings, a variant of the facade with molded details was adopted for the further development of the workshop building project. According to the technical project, the building area was 546 sq m, the cubic capacity was 5930 cubic meters, the height of the 1st and 2nd floors was 3.80 m and 3.83 m. In the explanatory note to the constructive part of the project, it was recommended to lay the foundations and outer walls of the basement with rubble concrete, the inner walls of the basement and the aboveground part of the building are brick. The partitions between the production rooms are designed brick with a thickness of 16 cm, partitions with a thickness of 10 cm are designed wooden from two layers of shields. The ceilings above the basement, workshops, bathrooms, stairwell and storerooms are designed with reinforced concrete, over the rest of the rooms – on wooden beams. The roof is covered with iron on a crate of beams. All the lintels, except for those separately specified, were designed precast reinforced concrete. The interior decoration of the premises was modest: the walls and ceilings were plastered with ordinary plaster and painted with glue paint, in the administrative rooms, cornices of a simple profile were stretched under the ceiling (according to templates), the ceiling in the lobby and, in the red corner, was finished with sockets. A mosaic floor was designed in the lobby, cement in the basement and bathrooms, and painted wood in the rest of the rooms. The steps leading to the lobby were mosaic, the steps of the stairwell and the marching platforms were designed with reinforced concrete. The doors on the main facade are designed oak, the rest of the doors and window sashes are pine. The construction of a two-storey building of workshops for consumer services was completed in accordance with the project of T. A. Komanina in 1953. In 1996, the building was restored with an adaptation for administrative use. The restoration and adaptation project was carried out in ODO "Dori" group.        </item>
        <item>The Dynamo stadium was built in 1934 and reconstructed in 1939. It was destroyed in the Great Patriotic War. The appearance of the existing building is the result of several stages of post-war construction and reconstruction. On 07.10.1944, the Council of People\'s Commissars of the BSSR adopted a resolution ""on the restoration of the stadium of the Belarusian Republican Sports Society ""Dynamo"", according to which it was envisaged to build a complex of sports facilities, including the main football field with stands for 15 thousand seats. The design of the Dynamo stadium and sports park was carried out at the end of 1944-1945 by architects V. B. Wolfensohn and N. E. Schmidt in the creative workshop of Academician M. Ya. Kolya (design and Technical Bureau of the Academy of Architecture of the USSR). Construction began in 1946, and already in 1947 the first stage of the stadium construction was completed, including the main stand for 12,000 people and a football field with athletics sectors. In 1948, 850 thousand rubles were spent on construction work, as a result of which the Dinamo Minsk stadium was already partially operated in the same year. The stands of the constructed stadium could accommodate 12 thousand spectators. With a norm of 10% of the number of residents of the city, the existing capacity of the main sports arena of the republic was clearly not enough for the capital Minsk. The population growth of the post-war city occurred at a rapid pace and this circumstance required urgent measures to prepare and conduct the next stage of construction of the stadium, thus, the stadium is designed symmetrical both along the longitudinal and transverse axis. All the sub-tribune space is used for the premises necessary for the normal operation of the stadium, as well as for the complex of sports halls and the premises of the Dynamo council. After the reconstruction and all the work carried out, the stadium is designed for 36800-37000 spectators. 02/23/1954 The Council of Ministers of the BSSR adopted a resolution “On measures to ensure the completion and commissioning of the Dynamo stadium in Minsk“, therefore, starting from the summer season of 1954, the stadium began to be actively used, although construction work has not yet been fully completed. For all the work done in the Union Competition for the best sports facility in 1956, the Minsk stadium took second place and received a diploma and a prize. The Dynamo Stadium in Minsk is the largest sports facility in Belarus, whose appearance reflects the main stages of the development of Soviet architecture of the post-war period.        </item>
        <item>The estate “Belaya Dacha" is located on the right bank of the Loshitsa River in the Minsk –Kurasovshchina microdistrict. According to the archival document, the plot on which the manor house was built, in the first half of 1911 The Minsk merchant Moisey Rogov bought from the Minsk resident Valentina Molodetskaya. On June 28, 1911, Candidate of Natural Sciences Moisey Yuryevich Rogov applied to the Minsk City Council for permission to build a stone one-story house with a tower in the Kurasovshchina tract. A plot plan and a house project were added to the petition. According to the project, the building had a complex asymmetric three-dimensional composition, which was completed by an octagonal tower covered with a hipped roof with a high flagpole. The whole building is covered with a roof of a complex configuration, and the facades had a rather expressive decorative solution. The main entrance to the building is highlighted by a massive wrought-iron canopy on columns. The cottage had a rather original layout. Through the front entrance one could get into the ""front room"", and from it into a large dining room, around which the main rooms were grouped. A bedroom, a living room and an office adjoined the dining room from the southeast. From the living room there was an exit to the outdoor terrace. A summer veranda adjoined the dining room from the southwest. In the north-western part of the building there were the main utility rooms: a kitchen, a maid\'s room and a pantry. Between the kitchen and the hallway there is a staircase that led to the tower. In the north-western part of the front there was an exit to the ""winter balcony"" decorated with stained glass windows. The project for the construction of M. Rogov\'s dacha was considered at a meeting of the Minsk City Administration on July 28, 1911. It was agreed and Rogov received permission to build a house. In late 1912 - early 1913 the cottage was already built. In the early 1920s, M. Rogov\'s dacha in the Kurasovshchina was nationalized and transferred to an agricultural school. In 1931, on the basis of this school, an experimental base of the Institute of Agrochemistry was created. After the Second World War, the building of the former dacha housed various services of the BelNII of Soil Science and Agrochemistry. During this period, the wooden terrace and the summer dining room were lost. In 1976, project work began on the restoration of the house under the direction of V. Slyunchenko. In 1978 a project was developed for the restoration of the ""White Dacha"" and the adaptation of the building for a museum of soil science and forest sculpture. (architect V. Atas). The project provided for restoring the original condition of the facades and layout as fully as possible. Additional space was required to accommodate the museum\'s exposition. The authors of the project were forced to go to the add-on of additional volume. As a result of the reconstruction carried out in the 1980s, the building of the ""White Dacha"" has changed its historical appearance. Later, until 2001, the building of the “White Dacha” was at the disposal of the Ministry of Culture of the Republic of Belarus. Art restoration workshops were located here, thematic events of the creative intelligentsia were held. The building was operated until about the mid-1990s. According to the Decree of the President of the Republic of Belarus No. 109 dated 26.02.2001, the building was transferred to the municipal property of Minsk. The Minsk City Executive Committee transferred it to the balance of the Department of Education of the Oktyabrsky district administration. In 2002 – 2004, a project was developed for the overhaul of the building of the former estate to accommodate the Out-of-school Work Center “Parus"". In accordance with the project in 2002 -2004 . repairs were carried out to replace stained glass windows, window and door joinery. The rest of the work was not completed due to lack of funding. The manor house is still not in operation. The building is a striking example of a country manor house of the early 20th century, built in the neoclassical style.        </item>
        <item>Freedom Square as an urban - planning ensemble began to form in the 16th century . This was facilitated by a large fire that occurred in 1547 and destroyed almost the entire building of the city. It was on the territory of modern Svobody Square that a new market was founded. At that time it was quite a large area – 220x140 m. All the main city streets converged to it. In the 18th century, the square was called the High Market, in the 19th-early 20th century. It was called the High Square, the Upper Market, Cathedral Square. The town hall and Gostiny Dvor were built in the center of the square, along the perimeter monumental buildings of Uniate and Catholic monasteries, noble palaces, houses of merchants and rich artisans. Town halls were the main buildings of most European cities. It was the location of the city self-government bodies (council or magistrate). The history of the construction of town halls in Belarus begins with the 15th century., when many cities received Magdeburg law. The town halls represented various combinations of two volumes: towers and buildings. The buildings of the town hall, as a rule, were two–storied, low, the towers were multi–tiered, high, with a clock and a bell - a symbol of independence and political freedom. The main room of the town hall was the magistrate\'s hall, there were also offices, treasury, archive. The lower and basement floors were usually used as storage rooms for storing goods. In the town hall there were meetings of the magistrate, courts, city celebrations, theatrical performances. The first mention of the Minsk Town Hall contains a deed of gift of the Grand Duke of Lithuania Alexander dated 14.03.1499 . to provide the city with self-government under Magdeburg law. The management of the city passed to the magistrate, but where the town hall was located at the beginning of the 16th century is unknown. The earliest information about the existence of a town hall in Minsk dates back to 1582. Since the 17th century, documents mention the town hall building located in the center of the square. It is known that the building was badly damaged in 1640, when the market with shops burned down. The Minsk City Hall, restored after the fire, acquired an expressive architectural appearance in the 18th century. the building fell into disrepair, but in 1744 it was restored on the initiative of S. Burzhinsky. At the end of the 18th century. provincial architect F. Kramer rebuilt the town hall, giving it the features of classicism. Probably, F. Kramer completely preserved the structural basis of the old building, only added the side and main porticos (the protruding part of the building with columns). Approximately such a town hall is shown in the plan of Minsk in 1793. In 1819, a stone fence was attached to the south-eastern facade of the town hall, a square was laid out. In the late 18th and early 19th centuries, the town hall building housed a court, a magistrate, a guardhouse, and an archive. In the 1830s, a music school was located here under the guidance of the famous Minsk musician-teacher V. Stefanovich. On holidays, the city orchestra often played in the open gallery of the second floor of the town hall. Since 1847, the city theater has been located in the building, the interior was decorated with a painting by the Minsk painter Ya. Kuryatkevich. In 1851, it was decided to demolish the town hall. Formally, the demolition of the town hall was justified by the fact that the building, occupying a part of the main square, restricts it and closes the view of the cathedral church. In 1988, a project for the regeneration of historical buildings within the boundaries of the International-Lenin-Bogdanovich-Svisloch Embankment streets was approved. The project provided for the restoration of the city hall building as of the end of the 18th century in the classical style. In 2002-2003, the town hall was restored according to S. Baglasov\'s project on a historical site determined as a result of archaeological research. On the second floor, where the magistrate previously sat, a hall for meetings and ceremonial receptions has been designed. On the ground floor, the project provided for an exhibition hall and an exposition dedicated to the history of the city.        </item>
        <item>The Main Post Office building is one of the most significant architectural structures of the first half of the 1950s in Minsk. With its architectural and stylistic essence, it truly reflects the time, life and artistic aspirations of the Belarusian people (cultural identity), who bore all the hardships of the Great Patriotic War of 1941-1945 on their shoulders and won. It is from this historical perspective that it is easier to understand and feel the architecture of the main post office, to feel the beauty of the world, the beauty of the people who created this wonderful architectural monument of the post-war period. In accordance with the general plan of Minsk, developed in 1944-46 at the Institute “Belgosproekt” by a group of Belarusian architects, the building of the Main Post Office took a responsible place in the structure of the central part of the city. The future architectural ensemble of the main thoroughfare – Sovetskaya St. (modern Ave.) began to form from it. Independence). The decision to allocate a site for the construction of a post office at the intersection with Sverdlov St. was made by the executive committee of the Minsk City Council on October 13, 1948. Design work was carried out in the “Belgosproject"" in the workshop of G. Zaborsky in 1949-1954. The author of the project is architect V. A. Korol. The design was carried out in several stages. At the beginning of 1949, a project assignment was developed. Then, on the basis of the project assignment in 1950-1954, technical and working projects were developed. The Main Post Office opened on March 28, 1955. The current state of the building indicates that it was erected in accordance with the prect. The building organically fits into the ensemble of Independence Square and the avenue. In 1970, the post office was reconstructed with a partial redevelopment of office premises. The reconstruction project was developed by architects A. Dukhan, Khat, engineer Pavlovsky. In 1980, stained glass windows with images of architectural monuments of Belarus were made in the main hall. In 2009-2010, repairs were also carried out.        </item>
        <item>In the early 1630s, the Bernardine convent appeared in Minsk, founded by Trotsky voivode, Minsk castellan Alexander Slushko. The exact date of its construction has not yet been established. Bibliographic sources and “visits of the monastery” of the late 18th century report different years of its foundation: 1630, 1642, 1645. The construction of the church most likely began in 1642-45, but it was not completed soon. But already in 1687 the consecration of the temple took place. In 1697, the stolnik M. A. Tolstoy, traveling through Minsk, saw both the stone churches of the male and female Bernardine monasteries already completed. During this period, most likely, a stone monastery building was built, since in 1740 this building, as follows from written sources, was no longer new. In 1741, after a fire, the church was reconstructed in the style of the Vilna Baroque. In an archival document of 1797 it is reported that ""the monastery and the church are stone... with them, wooden buildings""required repair. In 1835, the church was again significantly damaged after a fire.. In 1852, the Bernardine Convent for women was abolished, the last nuns moved to the Nesvizh Benedictine Monastery. In the following year , 1853 the entire estate land with the church and other stone and wooden buildings were transferred to the Holy Trinity Men\'s first-class Monastery transferred from Slutsk. In the early 1860s, the former church of the Bernardine Monastery was consecrated into an Orthodox church in the name of Cyril and Methodius. The monastery building houses a theological seminary with a college. In 1863, the buildings of the former Bernardine Monastery and the church were again damaged by fire, the roofs burned down. In 1868-70 . with the funds allocated by the Synod, the church and the residential building were overhauled: window frames and bindings were replaced, the floor was paved with ceramic tiles in the narthex. After the renovation and the final relocation of the monks from Slutsk, on January 4, 1870, a new monastery was opened, named in the name of the Descent of the Holy Spirit. In accordance with the decree of the Synod of May 11, 1870, in the same year, the main altar of the church was also consecrated on October 22 in the name of the Descent of the Holy Spirit, and on December 1 – in the name of Saints Cyril and Methodius. In 1918 The Holy Spirit Monastery was closed, the residential building was occupied by a fire brigade, a gym was made for it in the church. Since about 1929, transit prisoners have been kept in the basements. In the same years, the crosses were removed from the towers, icons and other church historical values disappeared. The Holy Spirit Church was revived in 1943: a new three-tiered iconostasis was erected, icons were brought, and the church was consecrated. After the closure of the Peter and Paul Cathedral On Nemiga, the pulpit and the miraculous icon of the Mother of God were moved to the monastery. During the Great Patriotic War, the vestibule to the northern wall of the cathedral was destroyed. In the early 1950s, repairs were carried out inside and outside so that the Cathedral could function. The Department for the Protection of Architectural Monuments drew attention to the need to restore the extension in order to return the temple to its historical appearance, as well as to install drying ovens, especially the northern wall. Major repairs were completed in 1955. In the 1960s, the interior was renovated, the limit of St. Barbara with a particle of her relics was created, the limit of the Kazan Icon of the Mother of God, the river with the relics of the righteous Sophia of Slutsk, the limit of Cyril and Methodius in the crypt. Restoration work was continued in the late 1970s and early 1980s. Especially valuable in the Cathedral of the Descent of the Holy Spirit is the icon of the Mother of God or the Minsk Hodegetria. It is also called the icon of the Most Holy Theotokos. It has been known for its miracles since ancient times. According to legend, it was brought by the Kiev Prince Vladimir Svyatoslavovich from Korsun and brought to the Church of the Nativity of the Virgin (Tithe). Despite the destruction of the shrine by Batu\'s troops, the icon survived. During the attack at the end of the 15th century . The invaders stripped the precious ornaments from the icon in Kiev of the Crimean Tatars, and the board with the image of the Virgin was thrown into the Dnieper River. On August 13, 1500, the icon miraculously appeared in Minsk near the Svisloch River near the castle. The townspeople noticed her by an unusual glow and brought her to the castle church of the Nativity of the Virgin. On October 18, 1616, on St. Luke\'s Day, the icon of the Mother of God was moved from the Castle Church to the church of the Holy Spirit Monastery. Since 1941, the icon has been located in the Church of St. Catherine (modern Peter and Paul) on Nemiga. At the same time, it was restored by the artist G. Vier. After the church was closed, the icon of the Mother of God was moved to the Holy Spirit Cathedral. In 1991-1992, on the initiative of the rector, Father Mikhail (Buglakov), the restoration artist of the first category, Peter Zhurbey, for the first time performed the restoration of the miraculous icon. Among the historical values worthy of special attention is the relic with the relics of the righteous Sophia, Princess of Slutsk, who after her marriage with Janusz Radziwill remained Orthodox. Thanks to her, the union of not Janusz and Kryshtof Radziwill supported Orthodox churches and monasteries, including in Minsk.        </item>
        <item>The Central House of Officers of the Armed Forces of the Republic of Belarus in Minsk was built as the House of the Red Army named after K. Ya. Voroshilov by architect I. Langbard. The project of the building was completed in 1933, and it was built in 1934-1937. The House of the Red Army included the old buildings of the bishop\'s compound of the 19th century. This greatly complicated the layout of the building and the organization of the architectural appearance of the structure. Its architecture is characterized by laconism and simplicity of compositional construction. According to the project, the building of the House of the Red Army contained numerous club and training rooms, recreation rooms, exhibition and other halls, a library, a restaurant, a developed complex of theater rooms with an auditorium for 1000 seats, a cinema concert hall for 800 seats, one of the best sports facilities at that time. The clear differentiation of the main premises and the presence of separate entrances made it possible to organize their independent functioning. The monumental and decorative design of the interiors was carried out by sculptors A. Bembel and A. Glebov. Bembel Andrey Anufrievich participated in the interior design of the House of officers in 1935 - 1936. Glebov Alexey Konstantinovich performed bas-reliefs in the Government House and in the House of Officers. These were his first works in Minsk. During the Great Patriotic War, the destruction occurred in the south-eastern wing of the House of Officers, i.e. the main destruction affected the concert hall. Design work on the restoration of the south-eastern wing of the building began immediately after the liberation of the city of Minsk in 1944. It follows from archival documents that captured German architects – Paul, Fix, Maar, Endrigat - took part in the design of the restored wing. However, later, in 1947, another project was carried out: the interior of the theater part was reconstructed according to a plan developed by a team of architects under the direction of G. Sysoev.        </item>
        <item>Victory Square together with Independence Square and pl . Oktyabrskaya occupies one of the main places in the composition of the main highway of Minsk – pr . Independence. The ensemble of Victory Square began to form in the late 1930s. At the initial design stage until the late 1940s, the area was semicircular. In 1939, in accordance with the general plan of Minsk, the construction of two semi-circular houses began. The ensemble of Victory Square received further development after the Great Patriotic War. Immediately after the liberation of Minsk in 1944 The Commission for Architecture Affairs under the SNK of the BSSR developed a draft of a new city layout, which was called ""a sketch of the layout of Minsk"". It became the main document according to which restoration work was carried out in Minsk in 1945 - the first half of 1946. At the end of 1944, on the basis of this sketch, the first post-war master plan was developed in the Belgosproject, approved in 1946. The second stage of the avenue from Krasnoarmeyskaya St. to pl. Victory was designed in 1947-50 . The author of the detailed layout of the pl . The winner was Professor M. V. Borsch. The square received a round shape and symmetrical layout. Until 1954, until the Victory Monument was erected in the center of the square, it was called round. Architecturally, the square is conceived as a gradual transition from free park spaces to an ordinary street. To do this, squares are laid out on both sides of the highway. The center of the composition of Victory Square is an obelisk located in the center of the square and having a height of about 40 m. In 1984, in connection with the laying of the first metro line, the square itself was slightly redeveloped and acquired an oval shape. Inside, all the rooms were plastered, except for the basements. The decoration of residential and office premises was modest: cornices of a simple profile were stretched and sockets were made on the ceilings. The interiors of the stores were made according to special projects. It should be noted that at all stages of the design of the ensemble of residential development of the quarters adjacent to the square. Of course, only the architectural and decorative solution of the facades was corrected. The architectural and planning solution of the entire complex remained unchanged. Residential buildings along the ave . Independence was connected by terraces with columns. Driveways to the courtyard from the side of the street . Zakharova and Frunze between the houses were decorated with gates with two side archways and shaped metal doors in the Central wing.        </item>
        <item>Design work on the construction of the terminal building began in 1945 . Architects A. P. Voinov, V. M. Varaksin, engineer Zisman worked on the project. In, G. V. Zaborsky also took part in the design of facades. In 1945-1946, the airport terminal project was developed. The building was designed elongated, two-storey. Facades from the side In 1946, design work continued. The technical design of the terminal building was developed. The basis was based on previous developments. Compositionally, the building was also solved as a two-story building. Certain adjustments were made to the decorative design of the facades, the main entrance part, and the side volumes. At the same time, in 1945-46, A. P. Voinov worked on a working project. The facades were completely redesigned in it. The central entrance part was solved by an arched portico (the protruding part of the building). Construction began simultaneously with the design work in 1946-47, then it was mothballed. The foundations, basement walls and a partially monolithic concrete floor over the basement were laid. Design and construction work on the terminal building was restored only in 1954. A. P. Voinov and G. V. Zaborsky, engineer N. Guleva worked on the project again. In 1954, a new project assignment was developed. it was recommended to decorate with stucco In the same 1954. after the approval of the project assignment, a technical project was developed taking into account the comments on the internal layout. Then, in 1954-57, a working draft was developed, according to which construction work was carried out. Livshits, Grudin, Belousov, Maklyatsova and others took part in the design together with G. V. Zaborsky and A. P. Voinov.        </item>
        <item>Immediately after the liberation of Minsk from the Nazi invaders in 1944, work began on the development of a ""sketch of the layout of Minsk"" and a new master plan. The master plan was approved by the Government of Belarus and the Committee on Spar Architecture under the Council of People\'s Commissars of the USSR in 1946. According to the master plan, the architectural ensemble of the center of Minsk initially consisted of three squares -Lenin Square (modern Independence Square), Central Square (modern Independence Square). Oktyabrskaya) and Kruglaya (modern Victory Square), united by an avenue. The central (Oktyabrskaya) square was to become the main part of this architectural composition. In 1944-1945, the first All-Union closed competition for the layout and construction of the central square of Minsk was held. In 1947-1948, a new closed All-Union competition for projects of the Central Square was held. Some proposals for the layout and development of the area were taken into account during further design and development. In 1951-1952, landscaping and backfilling of the territory, landscaping were carried out. A majestic monument to Stalin (17 m high) was erected on the square. After the formation of the October Square ensemble was completed, according to many researchers, it became obvious that not all aspects of the complex and interesting task of creating the square received the best solution. So, in particular, it was noted that the nature and location of the main final object of the square - the Palace of Trade Unions - was not quite successfully solved. The decision to allocate this land plot for the construction of the Palace of Culture of Trade Unions was made at a meeting of the Minsk City Executive Committee on 04.04.1949 . The construction period was also determined - 01.09.1949 - 01.01.1954 . The palace was built according to the reused project of architect V. Ershov. The Palace of Culture includes a spacious two-light lobby, a theater hall, a dance hall, rooms for the work of clubs, administrative offices. Over the years, the Palace of Culture of Trade Unions has not lost its functional purpose. In the first half of the 2000s, the interiors of the main rooms (lobby, auditorium, ""white"", dance halls, backstage) were restored. During 2008-2010, major repairs of the roof, facades, strengthening of the pedestals of six sculptural groups were carried out.        </item>
        <item>The building is located in the historical center of Minsk – the Upper Town. The appearance of the Musical Lane began to form in the 14th - 15th centuries . It is possible that initially it was a passage to the sites located in the center of the block formed on the eastern side of the former High Market square (modern Svobody Square). Then it became a passage that connected the square with Zybitskaya Street (modern Trading Street). In the 19th-early 20th century. the lane was called Bernardinsky, seminary, monastery (or little monastery), Musician. The building was given the name of the House of Freemasons. However, modern researchers have not found documents that would confirm that it was here that the lodge meetings took place. It is known that in Minsk there was a Masonic lodge “Northern Torch"" from 1816 to 1822. It is most likely that the building received such a name because one of its owners, Gilyary Stepanovich Yakubovsky, was listed in the lists of the Minsk Masonic lodge. The earliest information about the building dates back to the early 19th century . On the design plan of Minsk in 1817, which is largely fixed, a stone building is already shown on the site of house No. 5. It had a complex configuration in the form of an equi-pointed cross. According to archival documents, the house belonged to the merchant Troyan Klyuchinsky. In 1840, the heiress Anastasia Troyanova sold the house to the Zimnitskys. Franz Kazimirovich Zimnitsky rented the house to a Jewish school during 1849-1855. It should be noted that the new owner enlarged the existing building. An extension was made to the courtyard facade from the north side. After Constance Frantsevna Zimnitskaya, the area with the construction in 1898 passed to the nobles Aniela Stepanovna Lekast and Nedvedsky. Apparently, already new owners in the late 19th-early 20th century. on the courtyard facade, the right part of the house is being completed, as a result of which the building has received a rectangular shape. In this form, the building has been preserved to our time. In the inventory description of the real estate of the quarter for 1910, the building is characterized as a three-story building with a basement. However, a clarification was made that due to the slope of the terrain on the one hand it is two–storey, on the other - three-storey. In the column about the age of the house, it was indicated that it was 100 years old from the time of construction. This report also confirms the opinion that the house could have been built in 1810. In the early 20th century . the building functioned as an apartment building: several rooms were occupied by the owners, the rest were rented out. There were stone and wooden outbuildings on the plot, and a garden occupied the territory of the square on the right side of the house. During the Great Patriotic War, the building was preserved. Undoubtedly, the former Masonic house stands out among the residential developments of the Upper Town, forming its historical appearance. The building is one of the oldest residential buildings among the survivors in the Upper Town. The facades, despite the alterations, retained the features of classicism style architecture and, above all, the Venetian window on the second floor. In 2002, the building was restored with its subsequent use as a museum.        </item>

        <item>Ivan Dominikovich Lutsevich was born on 25.06. (07.07.) 1882 in the Vyazynka folvarka of the Minsk district of the Minsk province (now Molodechno district) in the family of a tenant. Childhood was spent on carts: Lutsevichi moved from place to place in search of rent. Only as a 16-year-old boy in one winter he graduated from the 2nd-grade Belaruch National School (1898). At first he helped his mother with the housework, and in 1903 he left his parents\' house. He worked as a traveling home teacher, a clerk for a judicial investigator in Radoshkovichi (1903), a junior clerk for a landowner in the present Sennensky district (1904), a trainee and assistant distiller on Brovary in the landlords\' estates in Semkovo near Minsk, Yakhimovshchina near Molodechno, Dolny Snov near Nesvizh (1905 – 1908). In 1908-1909 he was an employee of the newspaper, Nasha Niva, and at the same time a librarian at the library of B. L. Danilovich in Vilnius, studied at the general education courses of A. S. Chernyaev in St. Petersburg (1909-1913), at the University of Shanyavsky in Moscow (1915). Since 1913. Ya. Kupala is an employee of the Belarusian Publishing Society, editor of Our Field, (1914-1915). In January 1916, in Moscow, he married Vladislav Frantsevna Stankevich and in the same month was drafted into the army. He served in the road construction detachment of the Warsaw District of Railways in Minsk, Polotsk, Smolensk. In 1919, immediately after the proclamation of the Belarusian Soviet Socialist Republic, Yanka Kupala came to Minsk. Yanka Kupala actively participated in the creation of the BSU, the Academy of Sciences of the BSSR, the National Theater, republican publishing houses, was a member of the Belarusian Scientific and Terminological Commission, head of the literary and artistic section of the Literary and Scientific Department of the People\'s Commissariat of Education. On 13.06.1925, the government of Soviet Belarus awarded Yanka Kupala, the first Belarusian writer, the honorary title of People\'s Poet of the BSSR. The public activity of the national poet was quite intense. He took an active part in the creation of the Union of Soviet Writers of the USSR and the BSSR, was a member of the organizing committee of the USN of the BSSR (1933), was elected a member of the Board of the USN of the USSR (1934), a member of the Central Executive Committee of the BSSR (1935), participated in the VII All-Union (1935) and VIIII Extraordinary (1936) Congresses of the Soviets of the USSR, was member of the commission for editing the texts of the Constitutions of the USSR and the BSSR (1936). Yanka Kupala was elected deputy of the Minsk City Council (1929, 1939), deputy of the Supreme Soviet of the BSSR (1940). During the Great Patriotic War, he first lived in Moscow, then in PAS. Pechishchi near Kazan. The poet died in Moscow on 28.06.1942 . There are not unproven opinions that Kupala did not die of natural causes. Yanka Kupala was buried on July 1, 1942 at the Vagankovsky cemetery. 20 years later, in 1962, the urn with the ashes was transported to Minsk and reburied at the Military Cemetery.Ivan Dominikovich Lutsevich wrote under the pseudonyms Yanka Kupala, Yanuk Kupala, Marko destitute, Kupalsky Ya., , left,, Vaydelota, Yanuk from near Minsk, sluchchanin, ne-Gutnik, etc. The pseudonym of the poet Yanka Kupala was prompted by the most ancient legends about the flower-fern-the flower of happiness. The first known poem, My Share, in the Belarusian language dates back to 1904. The first published poem, the peasant, was published in the Minsk newspaper, North-Western Region, in 1905. the first collection, the pipe, was published in 1908. In St. Petersburg, then there were collections, Guslar, (1910),, the way of life, (1913). In 1908, Yanka Kupala wrote a poem , the eternal song,, in 1912 - ,Kurgan,, ,Dream on the mound,, ,Bondarovna,. During the 1920s – 1930s, the poet created a number of outstanding examples of Belarusian Soviet lyrics. At that time, his collections, heritage, (1922), ,Nameless, (1925), ,Song to Construction, (1936),,Order-bearing Belarus, (1937), ,from the heart, (1940) were published. For the last collection he received the USSR State Prize (1941). The poet\'s last poems were written during the Great Patriotic War. Yanka Kupala entered the history of Belarusian literature not only as a lyrical poet, but also as a playwright. In 1912, a comedy was written , Peacock,, in 1913 – ,scattered nest,, ,primaki,, in 1922 – ,Tuteishya,. Ya. Kupala is also known as a translator. He translated into Belarusian, The Word about Igor\'s Regiment,, the poem by A. S. Pushkin , The Bronze Horseman,, the works of T. Shevchenko, etc. Yanka Kupala wrote more than 1000 lyrical poems, 16 poems, 4 plays, about 150 journalistic articles. Ya. Kupala is a great songwriter of the Belarusian people, a classic of Belarusian literature, a poet, playwright and publicist, a deeply national artist of the word. Kupala \'s work became an artistic chronicle of the thoughts and hopes of the Belarusian people at the crucial historical boundaries of the first half of the 20th century . His work is defined by deep nationality, humanistic pathos. Numerous streets, educational institutions, scientific institutes are named after the national poet. Monuments, busts, commemorative steles in honor of the poet are installed not only in our country, but also abroad. A monument was erected in Yanka Kupala Park to mark the 90th anniversary of the birth of the Belarusian singer in 1972. It is oriented to Independence Avenue and creates the compositional center of the Park, organically combined with the museum building, the natural environment.</item>
        <item>"The planning structure of Ya. Kolas Square (until 1956 it was called Komarovskaya) began to form in the late 1930s with the construction of the building of the Institute of Physical Education here. In the early 1950s, design and work work were extended. Modern architectural planning by the author\'s team consisting of architects M. Borsch, L. Aranauskas, L. Matskevich. The 1952 project took into account and developed the steamed pre-war projects of 1939 (architect V. Muraveev) and 1940 (architect A. Klimov). Area (400x130 m). The north-West side of the square is formed by the industrial buildings of JSC ,MPOVT, (built for the plant of electronic computers named after R. K. Ordzhonikidze) and the printing plant named after Ya. Kolas. On the opposite side of the square there is the Philharmonic Hall building and on both sides of its life houses with built-in commercial and administrative-economic monuments, the Central Department Store building. The country\'s front universities are forgotten by the SOC building, the Olympic Games, and opposite multi-storey residential buildings. In the center of the square there is a square and a Monument to Ya .Colas. The monument to J. Kolas was erected in the center of the square in 1972 . in honor of the 90th anniversary of the birth of the national poet. Design work on the improvement and installation of the monument began at the Institute of Minskproject, in 1970. The project was carried out by architects Yu . Gradov, G. Zaborsky and L.Levin. The area was grown by a large fully-viewable parterre. In the center of the square there was a sculptural composition, which also included decorative pools, fountains. Group and single tree plantings and flower beds were used as components. So, for example, planting of a white willow (weeping willow) was provided near the pool. A two-tier dense group was designed near the monument: in the first tier -plum spruce, warty birch and red oak, the monument was oriented towards the avenue according to the project. The monument was executed by the sculptor, People\'s Artist of the BSSR (1944) and the USSR (1973), member of the Union of Artists of the USSR, acting member of the Academy of Arts of the USSR, academician of the National Academy of Sciences of the Republic of Belarus, Honored Artists of the BSSR Z. Azgur. Zair Isaakovich Azgur was born on January 2 (15), 1908 in the village of Molchan Sennensky district. In 1909, the family moved to Vitebsk. In 1921-1922 he studied at the private studio of Yu . M . Pan, then at the Vitebsk Art and Practical Institute. In 1923, Z. Azgur was enrolled in the sculpture department. After graduating from the technical school, Azgur went to Leningrad, where he studied at the Higher Art College (1926-1928). He pierced educational activities at the Kiev Art Institute and the Tbilisi Academy of Arts. Since 1923, he took an active part in exhibitions. In 1929, the sculptor returned to Belarus and was actively involved in the artistic life of Minsk. In the 1930s, for the Government House in Minsk, the Opera and Ballet Theater. During the 1930s and 1970s. the main genre in the work of Z. Azgur\'s portrait remained. The golden fund of fine art has forever included a brilliant gallery of portrait images of public, political figures, patriotic heroes, imagine creativity and the science of the intelligentsia. But not only the portrait genre attracted Z. I. Azgur. He has quite a captive pierced in the field of monumental sculpture: monuments, memorial complexes, ensembles. The most significant monumental work of the sculptor in the 1950s was the relief for the obelisk on Victory Square in Minsk. Monument Ya . Kolasu, tired on one square in Minsk, has become a symbol of Belarus. Azgur turned to the image of Ya. Kolas many times. As an artist\'s memory: I had to create a sculptural image of Yakub Kolas more than once, for the first time back in the 20s. Four times the poet\'s Lapis from nature. That\'s why I consider the work on the monument to the poet to be a routine topic that has passed, full, through all my life."" For example, in Vitebsk in 1924, Zair Azgur received orders for the city museum. Years the future sculptor met the poet for the first time, came to Minsk to perform a portrait from life. Since then, there have been friendly one-liners between artists and the poet. Yakub Kolas: , there was a lot of sensitivity and humanity in his attitude towards me,"" Researchers of A. Azgur\'s creativity will note the portrait of Ya. Kolas created by the master in 1949 (in 1958 made of a headset). It was already a half-figure, and not a bust in the usual sense. The poet is in a calm pose of reflection, his gaze is directed far ahead, according to the author, ... whether in search of whether he needs an artistic image for new poems, or in memories of the paths and tracts that he himself, along with thousands of Belarusian workers, went through his hard miles in life, ""The most significant work highlighted by the great master to the people\'s poet, undoubtedly, is a sculptural composition on ya.Kolas Square. About his vision of the monument to Ya. Kolas on the square in Minsk."</item>
        <item>Maxim Bogdanovich is a classic of Belarusian literature, poet, critic, publicist. Born on 27.11. (09.12.) 1891 in Minsk. The poet\'s father Adam Egorovich Bogdanovich (1862-1940) was an ethnographer and folklorist, a teacher. Mother Maria Afanasyevna pulp (1869-1896) died early when the future poet was five years old. Maxim spent his early childhood years in Grodno (1892-1896). Then he lived and studied in Nizhny Novgorod (1896 – 1908), Yaroslavl (1908 – 1916), where his father was transferred to the service. In Nizhny Novgorod he studied at the gymnasium, in Yaroslavl he graduated from the Demidov Law Lyceum (1916). The young poet came to his homeland for the first time in 1911. At the invitation of the editorial office of the newspaper, Nasha Niva, M. Bogdanovich visited Vilnius, met Vaclav Lastovsky, Anton and Ivan Lutskevich and other figures of the Belarusian Renaissance. The Lutskevich brothers invited him to stay near the town of Krasny in the Rakutevschina folvarka. Their uncle Vaclav Lychkovsky, the brother of their mother Sofya Emerikovna, lived there. M. Bogdanovich spent two summer months in Rakutevshchina. In the autumn of 1916, M. Bogdanovich moved from Yaroslavl to Minsk, where he worked as secretary of the provincial food committee. He settled in an apartment with Zmitrok Byaduli on Malo-Georgievskaya St. (the building has been preserved, moved from Tolstoy St. to Rabkorovskaya St., 19). Here he participated in the activities of the Belarusian Committee for Assistance to War Victims and the Belarusian House. In February 1917 Maxim Bogdanovich, seriously ill with tuberculosis, left for Yalta. There 12 (25).05.1917 died. Despite the fact that the poet\'s life and creative path was short, he occupies one of the most honorable places among Belarusian writers. The first work of M. Bogdanovich\'s allegorical narrative, Music, written in the style of a fairy tale-parable, was published in Our Field in 1907. Later in 1908, his lyrical poems were published. The poet\'s only collection, the wreath, was published in early 1914 (the title is 1913), which included poems written by him in 1908-1912. Themes of love for his people, stories are closely intertwined with love lyrics, sadness from the premonition of early death. Maxim Bogdanovich wrote poems, poems, short stories, critical articles and articles on the history of Belarusian literature. An important place in his work was occupied by translations of ancient, Russian and Western European authors. He was one of the first in Belarusian literature to master such complex poetic forms as tercins, Triolet, Octave, Rondo, sonnet, scherzo. Being far from his homeland, he studied the Belarusian language, sought to show its great figurative and pictorial possibilities. Russian Russian poet collaborated with many Belarusian, Russian, Ukrainian newspapers and magazines, his creative interests were multifaceted, he freely navigated the complex processes of Belarusian, Russian and other literatures. Maxim Bogdanovich\'s poetry has forever entered the spiritual treasury of the Belarusian people. Many of his works are set to music (songs, star Venus"", ""Slutsky Weavers"", ""chase"", opera, star Venus, (libretto by A. Bachilo, music by Yu. Semenyako). Streets in Minsk and Grodno have been named after Maxim Bogdanovich, museums have been created, monuments have been erected. A monument was erected in Minsk on 09.12.1981 to the 90th anniversary of the poet\'s birth. At first, it was installed in the park on Trinity Hill, in front of the Bolshoi Theater of Belarus. In 2008 , after the restoration , the monument was moved closer to M Street . Bogdanovich and to the place where the house in which he was born stood. The authors of the monument are the sculptor S. Vakar. architects Yu . Kazakov and L. Moskalevich. S. Vakar worked on the monument for more than ten years. The sculptural image of the poet is deliberately placed on a low pedestal in order to bring the poet closer to lovers of his work. In the figure of M. Bogdanovich, laconic plastic forms clearly convey the versatility of his nature, the exceptional attractiveness of his personality. The artist created a number of sculptural portraits of statesmen, heroes of the Civil and Patriotic War, among them Heroes of the Soviet Union M. A. Kedyshko, M. P. Shmyrev (parents of Minai) (1970), K. P. Orlovsky (1972), K. S. Zaslonov (1973), E. stickers (1974), figures of Belarusian culture: F. Skorina (1964), R. Borodulin (1965), V. Korotkevich (1968), P. Panchenko (1969), Ya. Kolas (1972), A. Kashkurevich (1975), Ya. Bryl (1976), G. Buravkin (1978), M. Gusovsky (1980), etc. The plastic precision of his works is combined with the depth and expressiveness of the images. Yuri Ivanovich Kazakov is a member of the Union of Architects of the USSR (1966). In 1964 he graduated from the Belarusian Polytechnic Institute (now BNTU). Main works (in the author\'s team): monument to the partisans in d . Ikany of the Borisovsky district (1965), V. I. Lenin in Lepel (1970), Stolin (1980), V. Z. Korzh in the village of Horstov of the Soligorsky district (1975), V. M. Azin in Polotsk (1976), S. Budnom in Nesvizh (1982), memorial complexes, Brest Hero Fortress,(1971), ,Dzerzhinovo, (1977), etc. He was awarded the Honorary Diploma of the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of the BSSR (1972). Leonard Viktorovich Moskalevich - Honored Architect of the BSSR (1985), member of the Union of Architects of the USSR (1968). In 1961 he graduated from the Belarusian Polytechnic Institute (now BNTU). He worked in ,Brestgrazhdanproject,, ,Minskproject,, in the office of the Central Committee of the CPB, Deputy Chairman of the State Construction of the BSSR. Main works (in the author\'s team): House of Political Enlightenment (1964), Brest Institute of Civil Engineering (1966), 647-apartment residential building at 78 M. Bogdanovich St. (1974), Music College (1975), Belarusian State University of Culture and Arts (1975), BelExpo, etc. He was awarded the Honorary Diploma of the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of the BSSR (1980).        </item>
        <item>The monument to Yanka Kupala in Minsk is a mandatory point of visit, included in many literary excursions, and enjoys enormous recognition among fans of this amazing poet\'s work. There are only two similar memorials to Yanka Kupala – the second, by the way, is installed in Moscow. A whole team of authors worked on the creation of this monument: sculptors A. Zaspitsky, A. Anikeychik, L. Gumilevsky and architects Yu. Gradov and L. Levin.
        For Soviet architecture, in all epochs, there was a tendency to scale and thorough solidity. As a result, it is not surprising that the monument to Yanka Kupala came out quite impressive in size. Its dimensions are slightly hidden by the trees that rise above the figure of this beloved poet. The monument to Yanka Kupala is considered the standard of Soviet architecture. The best tribute to the memory of the poet is a Belarusian word that has always sounded and will always sound at poetic meetings. Both the park itself and the Yanka Kupala monument of the same name are a true pearl among the emerald islands of the center of Minsk.        </item>
        <item>The military cemetery in Minsk belongs to the oldest necropolises of the city, many outstanding people of Belarus, state and party figures, soldiers, partisans and underground workers who died in the Great Patriotic War, scientists, writers, composers, actors and others are buried here. The military cemetery was founded at the military hospital in 1850 on a plot of land leased from landowner Eduard Stanislavovich Vankovich. Russian Russian troops won the Russo-Turkish War of 1877-78 in 1896-98 at the military cemetery designed by the Minsk diocesan architect V. I. Struyev in honor of the victory of the Russian troops in the Russo-Turkish War of 1877-78. The Alexander Nevsky Church was built, which has been preserved and operates. Around 1905, the cemetery was closed for burials. In the 1920s and 1930s, famous party, military, scientific figures, representatives of the creative intelligentsia were buried at the Military Cemetery. During the German occupation of Minsk, the deceased residents of the city were also buried here.After the Great Patriotic War, the territory of the cemetery was enlarged on the western side. 42 mass graves and more than 500 individual graves were organized in the new section of the Military Cemetery, in which more than 1,000 soldiers who died in battles with the Nazi invaders were buried. In 1921, the family returned to Minsk. Ya. Kolos worked in the scientific and terminological commission of the People\'s Commissariat of the BSSR, as a teacher at the pedagogical college and BSU. Since 1929, Vice-President of the Academy of Sciences of the BSSR. During the Great Patriotic War he lived in Klyazma, Tashkent, Moscow. In 1944 he returned to Minsk. Konstantin Mikhailovich Mickiewicz began his literary activity early. He wrote under the pseudonyms gushcha Taras, ogarok, lonely, Albutsky K, Andrey, socialist, Bulava Foma, nikolaevets, Nadnemanets, etc. He firmly entered the literature under the pseudonym Yakub Kolas. Of the early works of Yakub Kolas (1898 – 1906), about 60 were saved. the first published poem was called, our native land, and was placed in the newspaper, Our Share, in 1906. in 1910, a collection of poems, Songs of sorrow,, in 1912, a collection of prose, stories, and in 1914, native phenomena,. One of the most significant poems, Novaya Zemlya, and Symon-music, were written in 1911-1925. The poem, Novaya Zemlya, comprehends a whole epoch in the life of the Belarusian people. The 1920s were fruitful for the writer. The collections ,fairy tales of life, (1921), ,echoes, (1922), ,the first steps,, ,Step by step,, ,in quiet water,, , at the turn, (1922-1924), the story,in the wilderness of Polesie,, ,in the vastness of life, (1926), ,in the depths of Polesie,. In the 1930s, the novel, the renegade, (1930 – 1931), ,quagmire, (1932-1933), , in the forests of Polesie, were written. In the Great Patriotic War, the collections, revenge, (1942), , the voice of the earth, (1943), poem, Trial in the Forest, (1943),,Retribution, (1945) were published. For the cycle of poems of the war years, Kolas was awarded the USSR State Prize in 1946. In 1947 he graduated from the poem, Rybakov\'s Hut, for which he received the USSR State Prize in 1949. Yakub Kolas was extremely multifaceted in his creative activity. He wrote a lot for children, was the author of dramatic works, journalistic, literary-critical, scientific articles, translated into Belarusian the poem of A. S. Pushkin, Poltava,, works of T. Shevchenko, A. Mickiewicz, R. Tagore, etc. The national poet has left us a great legacy. All his works are imbued with a great and sincere love for his native land, for his native nature. The most significant moments in the life of the Belarusian people are reflected in the works of the writer with great vital truthfulness and skill. Yakub Kolas is known for his scientific and pedagogical activities. Participated in the establishment of the Belarusian State University, in the organization of the Institute of Belarusian Culture, then the Academy of Sciences, worked in many scientific commissions, compiling the Russian-Belarusian dictionary. He made a significant contribution to the development of the Bulorussian literary language. The writer took an active part in the public life of the country. In 1946-1956 he was elected a deputy of the Supreme Soviet of the USSR and the BSSR, was chairman of the Peace Protection Committee of the BSSR, a member of the Presidium of the Board of the Union of Writers of the USSR and the BSSR. The writer died on 13.08.1956. He was buried at the Military Cemetery next to his wife M. D. Mickiewicz. In 1959, the tombstone monument to Yakub Kolas was designed at the Institute, Belgosproekt, by architect L. Riminsky. The tombstone was designed from black polished labrador. It was decorated with carved ornaments. An obelisk made of solid stone was installed on it. The texture of the surface of the base of the obelisk was provided from ragged granite. A bronze sculpture of guslar was projected next to the obelisk. For reasons unknown to us, the monument designed by L. Riminsky was not installed. Only in 1970, a monument was erected on the grave of Yakub Kolas, made by Belarusian sculptors V. Ananko, M. Yakovenko and architect M. Myznikov.        </item>
        <item>"The Victory Monument was erected in 1954 on one of the main squares of Minsk, located on the main thoroughfare of the city – Independence Avenue. Until 1958, the square was called round. It began to form in the pre-war period in accordance with the general plan of Minsk, developed in 1932-1936 (architect Yu. kilowatts, consultant V. Wittman). After the Great Patriotic War, Minsk was restored and built up according to the master plan approved in 1946. Professor M. V. Borsch was the author of the detailed layout of the Round Square. Later this project was adjusted by G. Zaborsky and L. Matskevich. The reconstruction and development of the square was carried out in 1951-1956 . The square was solved symmetrically relative to the axis of the avenue, rectangular in plan 175x225 m, the central round part had a radius of 65 m. On the anniversary of the liberation of Minsk, July 3, 1945 The Supreme Council adopted a resolution on commemorating the victory and perpetuating the memory of soldiers of the Red Army and partisans who died in the fight against the Nazi invaders during the Great Patriotic War, the second paragraph of which indicated that a Victory monument should be erected in the capital of the Belarusian SSR - the city of Minsk ..., Then on May 14, 1946. A joint resolution of the Council of Ministers of the BSSR and the Central Committee of the CP(b)b No. 827-333/7 was adopted, On the improvement of the graves of soldiers of the Soviet Army and partisans and the perpetuation of significant places and events related to the Great Patriotic War on the territory of the BSSR,. The sixth paragraph of this resolution also referred to the construction of the Victory Monument in Minsk and the announcement of a competition for the monument project. According to the terms of the competition, the monument must be erected on the main square of the city, that is, Oktyabrskaya, must be solved by architectural and sculptural means, precious stones, bronze, stainless steel, etc. are used as materials. After it was decided to erect a monument to I. V. Stalin on the central (now Oktyabrskaya) square, on November 27, 1948, at a meeting of the Bureau of the Central Committee of the CP(b)b, a Round square was determined for the construction of the Victory Monument. December 21 , 1948 at a meeting of the Bureau of the Central Committee of the CP (b)b, it was decided to install a memorial plaque on the site of the future Victory monument by the 30th anniversary of the BSSR. On 30.08.1950, the Resolution of the CM of the BSSR No. 1098 was adopted on holding an open All-Union competition for the design of the Victory Monument on the Round Square. The same resolution approved the terms and program of the competition. A prerequisite was the design of the monument in the geometric center of the square. The jury of the competition was headed by the Chairman of the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of the BSSR V. I. Kozlov, the members were architect M. Parashnikov and sculptor Z. Azgur. Architects, artists and sculptors from Moscow, Leningrad, Riga, Stalingrad, Minsk, Gomel, Grodno, Brest, Polotsk, Mogilev and other cities of the Soviet Union took part in the competition, 71 projects were presented. The first prize was awarded to the project under the motto, Belarus,, the authors of which were G. V. Zaborsky and V. A. Korol. At the same time, the jury members noted that none of the awarded projects fully corresponded to the task of creating a majestic monument, with the exception of some valuable proposals in the project under the motto , Belarus,. According to the project, the monument was a four-sided obelisk with a height of 48 m, crowned with the coat of arms of the BSSR. The sides of the obelisk were decorated with decorative belts based on the Belarusian ornament. The obelisk stood on a stylobate. The upper part of the pedestal was decorated with thematic sculptural compositions. On January 2, 1951, the Resolution of the Council of Ministers of the BSSR was adopted based on the results of an open competition for the drafting of a monument-monument and an order was made to hold a closed competition for the development of the final draft of the monument. Six best authors from Minsk, Moscow, and Leningrad were admitted to participate in it based on the results of the previous competition. In addition to G. Zaborsky and V. Korol, Belarusian architects I. Rudenko, G. Benediktov, A. Hegai, and sculptor A. Bembel participated in the competition. The main provisions were determined for the participants of the competition: the monument should be solved by a high-rise composition (obelisk or column) or a three-dimensional one with a developed base, the height of the monument is limited to 40 m, the monument project should take into account the richness of Belarusian national art in its architectural design, reinforced concrete, granite, bronze, copper were offered as materials for the construction of the monument. The project of G. Zaborsky and V. Korol was recognized as the best. The following was reported about the results of the competition in the newspaper ""Zvyazda "":,...The authors sought to find the most expressive forms of the obelisk monument.
        According to the approved project, the monument will be a tetrahedral obelisk with a height of 45 meters, crowned with the Order of Victory and installed on a pedestal with a widely developed base in the form of approaches. In the lower part of the obelisk, bas-reliefs will be installed on four sides, which will reflect the great exploits of the Soviet people during the Patriotic War. The theme of the main bas-relief will reflect the apotheosis of the military exploits of the Soviet people. The second two bas-reliefs will show the moment of the solemn oath of the people\'s avengers-partisans and heroes-guards. The fourth bas-relief will reflect the heroic work of the victorious people during the war. The state emblem of the BSSR will be installed above the main bas-relief.The entire obelisk is decorated with Belarusian ornaments and inscriptions in a rhythmic manner. On the main side, inscriptions-slogans are cut down, on the rest – folk songs about the heroic deeds of Soviet people in the last war."        </item>

        <item>The building of the Opera and Ballet Theater was built according to the project of architect I.R. Langobard in 1935 – 1937, opened in 1939. Architect I.R. Langobard began working in Minsk in 1929. His first projects were the Government House, the District House of Officers. The theater building was designed by architect I. Langobard in 1932-1934 . The central core of the composition of the theater building was an oval hall with 3,000 seats in the form of a steep amphitheater with a large overhanging balcony. The main decoration of the auditorium was a large chandelier. The hall was surrounded by a semicircle of bright foyers on the first and second floors. The wardrobes were located in a wide front along the outer contour of the building in the lobby of the first floor. In a large volume and developed in terms of the stage part, adaptations for a quick change of scenery were provided. A lighting gallery was fitted around the entire circumference of the hall, under the ceiling.In accordance with the innovative functional program, the architecture of the building was also solved. This is a large building in terms of volume, located on an open space of a hill in a square. It had a centric, tiered composition. The visual part consisted of three cylindrical volumes placed one on one with seven projecting porticos of entrances.The stage box and auxiliary rooms were adjacent to the visual part with rectangular volumes. The walls are rhythmically divided by blades throughout the volume, each tier is completed with a horizontal belt, window openings are solved by vertical stripes between the blades. According to this project, the construction of the theater began in 1935. However, the conceived project was not fully implemented. The beginning of construction coincided with a period of changes in literature, art and architecture. The ideas of universal and actively mechanized theatrical action are criticized. Theater complexes of gigantic dimensions are considered inappropriate. These changes and the new strict regulations in the theatrical art led to the fact that the Lombard, without stopping the construction, had to rework the project. The auditorium was reduced to 1,500 seats with corresponding changes in the structure of the stage part. The capacity of the auditorium has been reduced by reducing its area and the number of seats on the balcony. It was already impossible to reduce the entire volume of the building to the new standard, resulting in a disproportion between the number of spectators and the volume of the theater. The office premises, especially the lobby group, turned out to be disproportionately large. During the Great Patriotic War, the theater building was damaged. A bomb hit it, reinforced concrete floors were partially destroyed. In 1944-48 the building was restored under the supervision of the author. The facades are newly plastered with terrazite plaster and painted in two tones, where white dominated. Lombard returned to the idea of decorating the facade with sculpture at the level of the second tier and in front of the main entrance. So, in the explanatory note to the restoration project it is written: “in accordance with the original project, to complete the intermediate semicircle (parapet). To make and install the facade stucco works specified in the project, such as: decorative statues in the central ones, bas-reliefs indicated on the project, stucco cartouches, large decorative vases on the sides of a large outdoor staircase and other elements in accordance with the project."" As a result, a decorative intermediate cylindrical volume projected at the initial stage between the volumes of the foyer of the second floor and the auditorium is being completed on the facades according to the Lombard project, but the installation of sculptures on the facades was abandoned. During the restoration, the audience hall was reconstructed. It acquired a classic structure: a parterre, two tiers of boxes and a mezzanine, rich in plastic, a solemn portal of the stage. There were boxes on both sides. In the interior design of the hall and foyer And . Langbard introduced decorative stucco, heraldry, pictorial symbols, giving them solemnity and theatricality. For example, regarding the decoration of the hall, the explanatory note recommended: “The interior decoration of the hall, such as a portal arch, a barrier of tiers, will be decorated with stucco works according to the project, which will be based on standard motifs of national character ornament.” The new portal consisted of 6 strips with stucco decoration. The coat of arms of the BSSR was placed in the center of the new portal. It was recommended to decorate the gaps between the arch openings of the lighting gallery with portraits of artists and literature. However, the final decision was different. Three vertical belts with images of musical instruments, various agricultural and industrial attributes were placed under the openings. Coffered ceilings were finished with molded rosettes, the ceiling of the auditorium was planned to be painted. The concretization of the theater\'s image takes place in the foyer, where the attributes of a classical theatrical performance (curtain curtain), visual information (bas-relief portraits of composers, mock-ups of productions, portraits of theater artists), restrained decorative details (capitals, stucco profiles) appear. According to the project, the side walls of the main entrance staircase were planned to be treated with decorative thin columns and mirrors between them. The walls of the Central foyer are made of stucco and paintings. The walls of the lobby were processed under artificial marble. In the semicircular lobby with two wardrobes, the ceiling plafonds were enriched with caissons. However, not all the interior elements conceived by Lombard were realized. Some decorative elements were lost during the reconstruction of the interiors in 1977-1981. (mascarons on the barriers of the boxes, stucco decoration of the columns of the hall, etc.). Since 1964, the process of rebuilding, repairs and reconstructions began, which increasingly distorted and worsened the external and internal appearance of the theater. In 1964-67 . to eliminate the leaks, instead of a flat roof, a slope was made over the volumes of the lobby, foyer, auditorium, stage box and backstage part. The reconstruction project of the building was developed by architects M. Baklanov and V. Ladynina in 1958. This seemingly simpler and technically primitive solution for the protection of floor structures and the organization of the drain greatly distorted the appearance of the building, solved in the principles of constructivism architecture. Inclined roofs, incompatible with the stylistic principles of constructivism, worsened its silhouette composition. In addition, window openings were made in the third tier of facades. In 1977-81, the interiors of the hall were reconstructed. The walls, ceiling, floor of stairs, lobby, foyer were lined with slabs of natural stone. At the same time, the artificial marble of columns, capitals, and stair railings made under Lombard was knocked down. In the auditorium, the stucco decoration of the railings of the boxes and balconies, the columns of the boxes were knocked down. The space-planning structure of the lobby group of rooms on the second and third floors and balconies has also undergone significant changes. From the general composition of the foyer of the theater, the rooms that are located in rectangular side volumes adjacent to the cylindrical volumes of the building are functionally and spatially torn off. The shape of the semicircular stairs to the hall on the second floor has been changed. Instead of separate flights of stairs alternating with platforms-pockets against the exits to the floor, a solid staircase was made. Also, solid stairs have been replaced with a staircase with columns and a platform in the foyer of the main entrance. In 1981, gilding works were carried out. The stucco decoration of the balcony railings has been restored and gilded in the hall. In 2005 the next stage of restoration of the Opera and Ballet Theater building has begun. The restoration and architectural solution was to restore the theater as an author\'s work of architect I. Langobard.In 2009, the reconstruction and restoration of the Opera and Ballet Theater building was completed.        </item>
        <item>Maxim Gorky National Academic Drama Theater celebrates its 90th anniversary. The theater is one of the centers of performing arts, an integral part of cultural life and a national treasure of the Republic of Belarus. It has its own special artistic appearance, stands out for the high level of acting performance, the originality of the director\'s interpretations, a deep approach to the development of the repertoire. The history of the theater, which is better known as ,Russian,, began in Bobruisk in 1932. The founder of the theater was Vladimir Kumelsky, an artist of a wide creative range and temperament. Russian Russian Theater of the BSSR was created thanks to him in Bobruisk on the basis of a traveling Russian drama troupe. In 1932, by the decree of the People\'s Commissariat of Education under the Council of People\'s Commissars of the BSSR, the theater was given the status, State,. From October 1933 to March 1934, the theater toured various cities. In 1933, his performances in Minsk were a great success. The play, Egor Bulychov, based on the play by M.Gorky (with Kumelsky in the title role) caused the delight of the audience and critics. At that time, Soviet dramaturgy prevailed in the repertoire of the theater: ,Chapaev, according to Furmanov, , The Death of the squadron, Korneychuk, , Raised virgin land, according to Sholokhov. Gorky\'s dramaturgy received special attention. From 1935 to 1941, after the end of the theater season, the State Russian Drama Theater of the BSSR worked in the building of the City Theater in Mogilev. In 1939, Vladimir Kumelsky died suddenly and Dmitry Orlov became the artistic director. He reorganized, and the theater staff was replenished with graduates of the Leningrad and Moscow theater schools. Only a small group of leading actors remained from the old cast. The Great Patriotic War temporarily stopped the creative life of the renewed collective, but despite the military events in the summer of 1943, the theater was restored in Moscow as a front-line theater. Without taking off their jackets and overcoats, the actors rehearsed, preparing for a meeting with the audience in the areas of Belarus that had just been liberated from the Nazi occupation. In 1944, the theater returned to the liberated Mogilev, and then settled in Grodno. Among the productions of the first post-war years: , Twelfth Night, W. Shakespeare, , Three Sisters, A.Chekhov, , Tsar Fyodor Ioannovich, A.Tolstoy. The high appreciation of the performances on tour in Vilnius and Minsk raised the question of transferring the theater to a permanent job in the capital. In 1947, the Russian Theater began performing on the stage of the District House of Officers, and in the spring of 1949 celebrated a housewarming party in the restored building on Volodarsky Street, 5, where it still works today. In 1955, the theater was named after Maxim Gorky, in 1994, for high achievements in the field of performing arts, the Maxim Gorky State Drama Theater was awarded the status, Academic,, and in 1999 - , National,.The repertoire of the theater was replenished with plays by Belarusian, Soviet and foreign playwrights. Since 1974, Boris Lutsenko has been the main director. A series of performances staged by him brought the theater true fame and well-deserved success not only in the Soviet Union, but also abroad. The event of the theatrical life of the country became his program performances, Macbeth, W. Shakespeare, ,Threepenny Opera, B. Brecht, , The Tragedy of Man, I.Madacha. The theater has acquired its own special face. Increased interest in moral and ethical aspects, comprehension of the essence of human existence, the struggle of good and evil were studied in the performances, To Go and not to return, by V. Bykov, , Return to Khatyn, by A.Adamovich, , The Last Instance, N.Matukovsky and others. The golden fund of the theater included a production of an Optimistic tragedy by V. Vishnevsky. In 1981, a small stage was opened in the theater. During this period there were performances of chamber sound: , On the Golden Lake, E.Thompson, , Dinner, J.K.Brisville. Lutsenko\'s performance, Perpetuum Mobile, or an Evening of Jewish Anecdote, deserved special appreciation. Since 1996, the theater has been working as a stage director Valentina Erenkova, who has staged such performances as, Secrets of the magic Attic, A.Erenkova, ,Papa, Papa, poor papa, you won\'t get out of the closet, you\'re hung by our mother between a dress and pajamas, A.Kopita, , Memories, M.Roshchina, ,Grooms, N.Gogol and others. In 2008, Sergey Kovalchik was appointed chief director of the Gorky National Academic Drama Theater. Before joining the theater, Kovalchik managed to accumulate a rich creative baggage. The performances in his production have repeatedly won the grand Prix of many international theater festivals. He managed to preserve and bring a new creative breath to the theater. His creative search was enthusiastically supported by actors of different generations, but especially by the youth of the theater. The performance, Running, based on the play of the same name by M.Bulgakov became an event in the cultural life of Belarus, was highly appreciated by critics and the theatrical community and received a diploma at the International Theater Festival, Panarama, in 2009.        </item>
        <item>The circus building was designed in the Belgosproject. The authors of the project are architect V. Zhukov, engineer Sapun, architects Nemchinova, Shpit and others took part in the design. The design work was carried out in several stages during 1954-1958. The circus building was designed in a complex with production and utility rooms, an economic yard, entrances and approaches to it. The layout of the building was developed in accordance with the program assignment, which lists the main groups of premises and requirements for them. So, for example, the height of the auditorium from the floor of the arena to the grate flooring should be at least 18 m, the diameter of the arena to the inner edge of the barrier mats should be 18 m, the width of the barrier of the arena - 0.5 m. according to the design assignment, an auditorium with an arena was designed on the ground floor. The diameter of the hall was 42.30 m . The seats in the hall are arranged in an amphitheater in a circle, only 15 rows. The hall had a stage platform, a platform for the orchestra, located on the axis of the main artistic exit above the main entrance to the hall. Around the auditorium, facilities were planned to serve the audience: a lobby with ticket offices, a cloakroom, a foyer, and couloirs. On the second floor, groups of rooms for the orchestra, administrative offices, boxes, foyers for artists and spectators, a buffet are designed. On the third floor there are service rooms for an electric lighting group, costume rooms, a rehearsal hall, etc. A stable with a rehearsal arena is designed in the basement. In the structural part of the project, it was recommended to lay rubble-concrete foundations, the walls and exterior columns are laid of brick, the floors above all the rooms are reinforced concrete, the dome is covered with wood, the roof is covered with galvanized steel. It was recommended to plaster the outside of the wall, to make the cornice and architectural details of precast reinforced concrete, to make mosaic exterior steps in front of the entrance. In the architectural design of the facades, the authors used order plastics: portico, pilasters, cornices, portals, sandrikipo type installed on the avenue.According to the documents, the construction of the circus was started on 10/30/1954. The construction work was carried out by the staff of the 4th department of the Trust No. 2 of the Ministry of Urban and Rural Construction of the BSSR. As of February 1955, a foundation pit had already been dug and concrete blocks were being laid. In the summer of 1956, workers completed the installation of the amphitheater, the third floor was built of brick. By May 1958 the main construction works were completed, internal plastering was carried out, the floor was laid, sanitary and electrical work was carried out. The finishers of the trust No. 17 joined the work. the seats for the auditorium were made by special order in Ruzhany at the local district industrial plant. Special equipment for the premises was presented by enterprises in Moscow, Tbilisi, Kharkiv and some other cities. All works were completed on December 30, 1958, the act of delivery and acceptance was signed on 02/16/1959. In 2009-2010, reconstruction and restoration of the circus building was carried out. As a result of these works, the decor in the interiors of the foyer, lobby, auditorium, amphitheater, and on the facades of the building was preserved and restored. On the east side, a new volume, designed in a modern style, is attached to the existing building. In addition, the reconstruction project provides for the redevelopment of the auditorium complex: the ticket office lobby and ticket offices are located in a separate building, the cloakroom for spectators has been moved to the basement floor, a bypass corridor around the arena for artists has been made, the entrance lobby has been expanded, on the second floor there are foyers, two guest boxes and VIP boxes with a separate foyer, wardrobe, buffet and a bathroom, on each floor there are buffets at the ends of the foyer.        </item>
        <item>Immediately after the liberation in 1944, work began on the development of a new master plan for Minsk in 1945. The main provisions for drawing up a draft design of the layout and development of the central part of Minsk and the architectural solution of the main squares and the main thoroughfare of Sovetskaya Street were approved. Among the main buildings that were proposed to be placed on the main thoroughfare of the city, the Philharmonic building was also named. The cubature of the Palace building changed slightly, alterations concerned to a certain extent the structural part and redevelopment, taking into account the specifics of the Philharmonic, the main attention was paid to the concert hall, especially its acoustic qualities, the overlap over the concert hall was maintained according to the main project, but additional suspended structures made of sound-absorbing materials were allowed.Also, in order to improve acoustics, the interior of the hall and stage was interpreted by the authors as a single whole space. therefore, the erected side parts of the portal on the stage were dismantled\' a concrete beam above the portal and a brick wall on it\' separated the hall from the stage. The stage itself was designed anew as a stage-bandstand. Its back part was reserved for the installation of the organ. The layout and design of the balcony was changed, its removal over the ground floor from the transverse wall and from the side walls was reduced. The reinforced concrete columns that held the balcony and were placed in the hall were replaced with less bulky ones. This solution of the balcony, according to the authors, improved the overall appearance of the hall and increased the number of seats. It should also be noted that according to the new project, two additional stairs for evacuation communication of floors were located at the outer walls of the main facade. And already erected front semicircular stairs connected the foyer, 1st floor with a balcony. In addition, they were supplemented with marches to climb from the basement to the 1st floor. The main groups of premises were distributed as follows. On the ground floor there were cloakrooms, bathrooms, utility rooms, workshops, on the ground floor there was a concert hall, a buffet, couloirs, on the second administrative premises, artistic costume rooms, on the third rehearsal classrooms, a hardware room, etc. the authors of the project paid attention to the reliable sound insulation of the rehearsal rooms from the concert hall. According to the interior design, the project proposed to treat the walls of the concert hall with high-quality plaster with glue paint, use plastic and metal in the design of the balcony, decorate the parapets with decorative ornaments, sew the ceiling with aluminum sheets, parquet floor. In 1984, a five-storey administrative and household building was attached to the end wall of the Philharmonic building, the extension project was developed in the Belgosproject by an author\'s team consisting of architect L. Khayutin, engineer Y. Kiryushchev, designer V. Kontarovich in 2002-2004. overhaul of the philharmonic hall building with modernization of interiors).        </item>

        <item>The suburb of long ford arose at the beginning of the X XX century. at the intersection of the Mogilev tract with the Slepny River (modern Botanic and Kozlov streets), which was overcome in the ford. Originally, the cemetery was located at the end of Hospital Street. The first burials on it date back to 1853, when soldiers and officers who died in the Crimean (18531\') and Russian-Turkish (1877-78\') wars were buried here. In 1895, due to the filling of the territory, the cemetery was closed for burials. A new territory was allocated nearby, called the new Military Cemetery, which was consecrated on July 2, 18951\'. Two paths arranged in the form of a cross divided the territory of the cemetery into four parts. Each of these units was allocated for the burial of soldiers of two infantry regiments, artillery and local battalions. Over time, in order to perpetuate the memory of the soldiers who died in the war of 1877-78, a memorial temple was supposed to be built in the center of the cemetery. April 13, 1896. The provincial engineer Nektoryevsky provided a drawing and an estimate for the construction of the church to the Construction Department of the Minsk Spiritual Consistory. At a meeting of the Construction Department of the Minsk Provincial Government on April 16, 1896, the project was approved and the estimate was approved, total construction costs amounted to 11227 rubles 39 kopecks. Archpriest Pavel Filippovich Bogdanovich, dean of the 30th Infantry Division, and Kiriak Pavlovich Burdin, a veteran of the Russian-Turkish War, a participant in the legendary defense of Shipka, took an active part in the construction of the temple. the construction was completed by the beginning of 1698.On February 2, 1898, His Eminence, His Eminence Simeon Bishop of Minsk and Turovsky consecrated the newly built church in the name of the Holy Prince Alexander Nevsky, the Vilna Governor—General and Commander of the Vilna Military District, Adjutant General, General from the Minsk Province, Lieutenant General, Prince N.N., Trubetskoy took part in the Celebration. Commander of the 4th Army Corps, Lieutenant General P. T. Perlik and other high—ranking officials. The Alexander Nevsky Church received the status of the regimental church of the 119th Infantry Kolomna Regiment In February 1938, the authorities ordered the church to be closed. Until July 1941, a lock was constantly hanging on the doors of the church, Services were not held. But the church building has never been used for any other purpose other than the liturgical one. On July 24, 1941, during the bombing of the area adjacent to the Military Cemetery, one of the bombs hit the temple, destroying the central dome. In the first years of the war, the roof was repaired, but the restoration of the central dome of brick took place only many years later. The Executive Committee of the Minsk City Council of People\'s Deputies gave permission to carry out proper work, provided that: ". . .. all work must be carried out at the expense of a religious association." In December 1978, the work on the water supply and sewerage of the church building was completed. in 1980-81, the necessary documentation was developed and agreed upon for the restoration of the central dome of the church, destroyed in June 1941. In 1982, during the Council for Religious Affairs of the Byelorussian SSR, 16 tons of bricks produced at the Lode drainage pipe plant of the Latvian SSR were purchased for restoration work. In the same year, the restoration of the exterior walls, roof and domes of the church was carried out. In 2003, due to the failure of the old water supply system, work was carried out to ensure the water supply of the church by tapping into the municipal water supply system along Krasnozdnaya Street. In August 2010, together with the Department for the Protection of Monuments of the Ministry of Culture of the Republic of Belarus, the Parish Council of the church signed a security obligation for the material and cultural value of the historian, which is the building of the Alexander Nevsky Church, built in 1898.        </item>
        <item>A plot for the construction of a residential building was allocated to the Minsk Molotov Plant in accordance with the decision of the Minsk City Executive Committee. The plot is located near the former Catholic cemetery. The architectural and planning assignment for the design of a 200-apartment residential building of the State Union Plant No. 281 named after V. M. Molotov was approved in 1950. In accordance with the design assignment, the building was designed along the red line of the development of ul. Sovetskaya (modern ave. Independence). The height of the building was determined at 5 floors, however, it was stipulated that ""a partial increase or decrease in floors is possible due to the overall architectural composition."" In the gap between the Projected building and the neighboring house on Dolgobrodskaya St., according to the design assignment, it was proposed to make a retaining wall with small architectural forms. The design assignment emphasized that the nature of the architecture and decoration of the building should correspond to the construction of the main thoroughfare of the capital. It was recommended to provide for the treatment of the base with natural stone, to plaster the walls with high-quality colored plaster or to cover them with slabs. It was recommended to take a typical Kovykov section as the basis of the planning solution. The project for the construction of the house was designed by architect M. V. Borsch. According to the project, the building was divided into three buildings by two passages. The first building was located along Sovetskaya and Dolgobrodskaya Streets, had 5 floors with a kindergarten on the ground floor. Building No. 2 was located on Sovetskaya Street, had 7 floors, shops and household workshops were designed on the ground floor. The third building was located along Sovetskaya and Krasnozdnaya Streets, had 5 floors with shops and a kindergarten on the ground floor. The corner part of the building on the sides of Sovetskaya and Dolgobrodskaya Streets was designed as a dormitory for temporary visitors to the plant. On the ground floor there were rooms for a porter, a storage room, an office, a buffet. On the other floors there were 8 rooms, bathrooms and a small living room. Due to the functional change of the corner part of the building, the number of apartments in the house was changed. According to the new solution, 180 apartments were designed in the house. Some changes have also occurred in the functional adaptation of the first floor. In the central part of the building, after the project was adjusted, a photo studio, a savings bank, an atelier, a barber shop, a bookstore and an advertising agency were to be located. The premises allocated for the savings bank were located between two stairwells. According to the project, the floor in the operating room was planned to be made mosaic, in the office premises - from boards. The large display window in the operating room had a similar solution to the display windows in the other rooms on the ground floor of the building.        </item>

        <item>Trostenetsky death camp is the largest death camp in the occupied territory in Western Europe. In terms of the number of victims, it ranks fourth after Auschwitz, Majdanek and Treblinka. According to one data, 206,500 people were killed in the camp, and according to the information of the Emergency Commission established after the liberation of Minsk in 1944, more than 546,000 people were killed. These are prisoners of war and Minsk underground workers, partisans of Belarus and civilians, prisoners of the Minsk ghetto and many thousands of people from France, Austria, Germany, Poland, the Czech Republic, Slovakia. The Trostenets death camp unites several places of mass destruction of people: the Blagoveshchyna tract is a place of mass executions, the camp itself is near the village of Maly Trostenets at a distance of 10 km from Minsk along the Mogilev highway, the Shashkovka tract is a place of mass burning of people. The Blagovshchina tract, located on the 11th km of the Mogilev highway and 1.5 km from the village of Maly Trostenets, was chosen by the occupiers as a place of mass destruction of people in the autumn of 1941. The first echelon arrived here from Germany from the city of Hamburg on November 10 , 1941 . 990 people were delivered, most of them were immediately sent to Blagoveshchyna for destruction. The rest were sent to the Minsk ghetto, where since the summer of 1941 there were already about 80 thousand Minsk Jews. By the end of November 1941, 6 more echelons arrived from Germany, Czechoslovakia and Austria. In the autumn of 1943, the outcome of the war became obvious and the Nazis began work to destroy traces of their crimes. Using the labor of prisoners of the Minsk prison in November-December 1943, about 100 thousand of those shot in the Blagoveshchyna tract were excavated and burned. Residents of the surrounding villages were forced to deliver several thousand cubic meters of firewood for this. 34 pit graves up to 50 m long were found in the tract. The actual concentration camp near the village of Maly Trostenets was created by the fascists at first as a worker on 200 hectares of the pre-war collective farm named after K. Marx. As a result of the information collected immediately after the liberation of Minsk in July 1944. The Extraordinary State Commission to investigate the crimes of the Nazi invaders in the occupied territory, the memoirs of witnesses, materials collected by the staff of the Museum of the History of the Great Patriotic War and survey work on the territory of the death camp ""Trostenets"" in 2002-2004. it can be argued that the objects of the labor camp in Maly Trostenets were built since the spring of 1942. Construction began with the construction of premises for the commandant and security, and a year later a large number of structures for various purposes were erected here – a 2-storey house for security services, a warehouse for grain preservation, an asphalt plant, a sawmill, a mill, various workshops – sewing, shoemaking, carpentry, locksmith. The territory of the camp included two zones -one for workers and the other for prisoners sentenced to execution. The camp was surrounded by barbed wire under electric current. Towers were built for protection. The prisoners lived in wooden barracks. To organize the entrance to the camp from the Mogilev highway, a road lined with poplars was laid (partially preserved). By rail since the spring of 1942, 2 times a week, foreign citizens were brought here for the destruction. Things were taken away from the arrivals. The prisoners suffered from cold, dirt, and hunger. In October 1943, for the destruction of corpses shot in the village of Shashkovka, a cremation furnace was built -a pit measuring 8 sq. m and 4 m deep . Rails were laid parallel at the bottom of the pit, and an iron grate was placed on them. The executions were carried out directly at the entrance to the furnace. The corpses were put on rails, shifted with firewood, watered with a special combustible mixture and burned. The furnace was surrounded by a high board fence (3 m) and barbed wire. The ashes from the furnace were used by the Nazis as fertilizer for fields located in the area of the camp of a subsidiary farm belonging to the security police department and SG. By June 1944, more than 50 thousand people were burned in the furnace. An obelisk in memory of the dead was installed on the site of the furnace. Many prisoners were destroyed during transportation to Trostenets in gas cars. Almost every day, 4 such cars came to the concentration camp from the SG, in which 100-120 prisoners were loaded. From 17 to 25 February 1943 Thus, 2 echelons of prisoners were destroyed – about 3,000 people The Trostenets death camp was liquidated on July 3, 1944 during the liberation of Minsk. By the resolution of the CM of the BSSR of 19.01.1950, No. 1629, the former death camp ""Trostenets "" was listed as a monument of history and architecture of republican significance. In accordance with the Resolution of the CM of the BSSR of 08.04.1959 . No. 248 ""On the improvement of burial sites of soldiers of the Soviet Army, partisans and civilians who died in 1941-1944, and on the perpetuation of significant places and events related to the Great Patriotic War on the territory of the BSSR"" in 1963, an obelisk with an Eternal Flame was installed near the village of Bolshoy Trostenets, in 1965 an obelisk was erected on the site of Puni, in which prisoners were shot and burned (reconstructed in 1983), in 1966 an obelisk was erected on the site of the furnace pit. In 2002, a memorial sign was installed in UR. Blagoveshchina. 27.06.1994 The Resolution of the BSSR Council of Ministers No. 473 ""On the creation of a memorial complex"" was adopted In 2010. The design documentation for the construction of the 1st stage of the Trostenets Memorial Complex was developed in the UP "Institute "Minskproekt".        </item>
        <item>"The fascist camp near the village of Masyukovshchina was established at the end of August 1941 on the site of dulag-130, which was founded in July. The camp was located near the Minsk-Molodechno railway, on the site of a military camp where a cavalry unit was located before the war.For the needs of the camp, 21 wooden buildings were adapted for barracks, designed for 9.5 thousand people, outbuildings for car workshops, garages. The territory of the camp was surrounded by barbed wire, watchtowers and searchlights were installed. The external security of the camp had 15 posts, and the internal - 29. the camp was guarded by 135 people. In 1941-1942, prisoners of war erected residential and outbuildings on its territory. The camp was headed at different times by commandants: Majors M. Osfeld and G. Linsbauer, Colonel M. Postnik. At the beginning of July 1941, Dulag-126 was organized here. Prisoners of war who were hijacked here were placed in a vacant lot. Three barracks were occupied as a camp infirmary. The residence of the district commandant of the prisoner of war camps, Lieutenant Colonel Voltke, was also located here. The main part of stalag-352 was a forest camp. Prisoners of war who arrived here by train were met by camp guards with shepherd dogs and sorted them.The camp was divided into separate compartments -officers, Ukrainian, national minorities, Russian, Jewish. Each barracks in the compartment was fenced with barbed wire. The passageways and passageways inside the camp were called streets, and each of them had a name. Warm clothes and leather shoes were taken away from the prisoners who arrived. In return, they were given worn shoes with wooden soles and clothes from the dead and the dead. Some of the prisoners were housed in barracks of 400-500 people each. Most of them remained in the camp under the open sky. Many of the prisoners of war were freezing. There was also no way to hide from the cold in the destroyed barracks. The daily ration of prisoners of war in the camp consisted of 80-100 grams of ersatz bread and two cups of balanda. The death rate of prisoners from cold, hunger and beatings reached incredible proportions. Every morning, 100-150 corpses were pulled out of the shed, which were dumped into a common pit. In addition to hunger, prisoners of war were brought to exhaustion with all kinds of punishments. The worst of them was the punishment cell, measuring 1.5 × 2 m, and at a height of 1.3 m, barbed wire was thickly stretched in it so that the prisoner of war could not stand. There was no roof in the punishment cell, there was no way to hide from the weather. The punishment in the punishment cell lasted 3-5 days, food was given out once every 3 days. As a rule, corpses were taken out of there. Beating with batons, whips, wire whips, ramrods remained an expanded form of punishment. The guards fired rifles and machine guns at prisoners of war who were passing through the camp, poisoned them with dogs. It was not without mass shootings. In December 1941-March 1942, 200-300 people died daily in the camp, and on some days up to 500 people. In November-December 1941, 25 thousand people died in a forest camp. prisoners of war, in December 1941-April 1942 - about 30 thousand people, in the city camp in the Pushkin barracks in October 1941-January 1942 - 10 thousand people. Special teams of orderlies took the corpses to the burial site, put them in pits, and buried them only in the spring. The medical service was headed by a German from the camp administration, and the chief doctor of the infirmary was a Russian Tarasevich. In July 1942 The medical and sanitary service consisted of 50 doctors, 46 paramedics, 19 nurses and 92 orderlies. Almost all medical personnel consisted of prisoners of war. The camp infirmary was designed optimally for 4,200 beds, with a maximum of 5,000. The infirmary received Soviet-made medicines and medical instruments - captured trophies taken from prisoners of war who crawled into the camp. There were not enough medicines and the medical staff used the methods of traditional medicine. But even this did not save from high mortality. In January 1942, 6260 patients were admitted, 1711 of them died, in February 1173 out of 4573 people died. In the spring of 1942, the situation in the camp changed, as labor was needed for the military economy. By the summer of 1942, all prisoners were placed in barracks. In the same year, a hospital, a bathhouse and a sanpropusnik were established in the forest camp. The daily bread ration has increased to 270 grams. Back in 1941, teams were formed from prisoners of war to work both inside and outside the camp. In the camp, they repaired, built, harvested firewood, cleaned the territory, brought water, worked in the garage and workshops. The largest applicant for labor from the camp was the military construction ""Tota organization"", which used prisoners to dismantle ruins in the city, at enterprises, construction of facilities, bridges. German newspapers ""Novoye Slovo"", ""Klitsch"" and others published in Berlin were distributed in the camp. Their main content is the defeat of the Red Army at the fronts and the victories of the Wehrmacht. There were also ""volunteers"" who saw in cooperation with the Germans a way out of a difficult situation. Those selected and willing to cooperate with the Germans were improved nutrition, they were sent to courses to study amphibious warfare, methods of sabotage and espionage. Among them were those who sought to use enemy formations to save themselves and switch to the side of the partisans and the Red Army. Most of the prisoners of war were hostile to the Germans. Memories of the Motherland, news of the victories of the Red Army helped the prisoners to find the strength to spiritually resist violence and humiliation of their human dignity. Bathhouse and sanpropusknik, where prisoners M. Ts. Martynov and E. F. worked. Mikhnenko, were a kind of propaganda point. Here they learned all the news from the life of the camp and about the situation on the fronts. In the garage, the prisoners managed to assemble a radio receiver and sometimes listen to the voice of Moscow. The Nazis brought prisoners of war to the camp from the areas bordering Poland, from the territory of Belarus, from near Vyazma, Rzhev, Kalinin, Moscow, Stalingrad. More than 100 thousand prisoners passed through the camp. Stalag - 352 was considered by the Nazis as a transshipment base on the way of prisoners of war to the camps ""Ostland"", the general government of Poland, Germany. More than 80 thousand Soviet prisoners of war died in stalag-352. they were buried in 197 grave pits in a cemetery 400 m south-east of the camp near the village of Glinishche. In June 1944, the stalag-352 liquidation team arrived in Minsk. By order of the commandant of the city, its evacuation began on June 3 with the removal of camp property and lasted until June 26. On June 26, the prisoners were taken out. The transport with prisoners of war and the infirmary moved through Molodechno, Parafyanovo, Vilnius. In Vilnius, the route of the train was changed and sent to Dulag-230 In Alytus, and from there moved to Milov, Poland. In 1949, a monument was erected at the burial place of the prisoners. Together with the evacuated camp, apparently, the documents of stalag-352 were also taken out, since only in the infirmary of the camp were found lists of the deceased and individual medical histories, according to which it was possible to establish the names of more than 9 thousand people. prisoners. In 1965, these names were printed in the book ""Eternal Memory to you, Sons of the Soviet People"", published in four copies, stored at the memorial complex in Masyukov region, at the burial site of prisoners of war, and in the Belarusian State Museum of the History of the Great Patriotic War. Not earlier than July 3 , 1944 . On behalf of the Extraordinary State Commission, a special forensic medical expert commission consisting of the chief forensic medical expert of the People\'s Commissariat of Health of the USSR, Director of the State Research Institute of Forensic Medicine of the People\'s Commissariat of Health of the USSR V. I. Prozorovsky; Professor of the Department of Forensic Medicine of the 2nd Moscow Medical Institute, Doctor of Medical Sciences V. M. Smolyaninov and consultant of the Moscow city forensic medical examination of Dr. P. S. Semenovsky conducted a forensic medical examination based on documentary materials about stalag - 352 and the infirmary at this camp. Circumstances of the case: during the temporary occupation of the BSSR in the vicinity of the mountains. Minsk, on the territory of the military camp, the German command organized a camp for Soviet prisoners of war, which was called Stalag-352. this camp existed for 3 years (from July 1941 to July 3, 1944 - the Day of the Liberation of the mountains. By the Red Army). After the expulsion of the Nazi invaders, the Extraordinary State Commission found, judging by the calendar dates, only part of the medical documents - medical histories, certificates, certificates, death reports and other documents in the premises of the camp. Some former Soviet prisoners of war who were held in this camp accidentally managed to escape. In their testimony, they describe the terrible circumstances and regime that existed in the camp. Expert opinion on documentary materials. A special forensic medical examination examined: a) 4520 medical histories of the camp infirmary; b) certificates, certificates, reports and other documents related to the identification and registration of diseases, as well as causes of death in 9425 Soviet prisoners of war. The infirmary at stalag-352, judging by the identified documents, consisted of a number of departments: distribution, surgical, therapeutic, infectious and typhoid. In the distribution department, of the group of sick Soviet prisoners of war who came from this camp, a significant part were in such a serious condition from exhaustion that the patients died already in the distributor itself. There were patients in the surgical department due to gunshot wounds, blunt force injuries and other objects, as well as burns and frostbite. However, based on the documents, it was established that, as a rule, colitis, hemocolitis, dystrophy developed widely in patients of the surgical department, and patients died from exhaustion. Infectious and therapeutic departments received patients from the camp due to colitis or hemokalitis, as well as due to protein-free (starvation) edema, tuberculosis, pneumonia, stomach ulcers and other diseases."        </item>
        <item>"Jewish ghettos are essentially death camps. They were part of the Nazi policy of genocide aimed at the extermination of people on racial, national and religious grounds. The Minsk ghetto was created on July 19 , 1941 by order of the commandant of the field Commandant \'s Office No. 812 K. Schlegelhofer. The area allocated for the ghetto had an area of about 2 sq. km. The ghetto boundaries included the quarters of zachishchai, Rakovsky suburb, Jubilee Square and the quarters adjacent to it. In total, about 40 streets and alleys were allocated for the ghetto, on which there were 273 mostly wooden one- or two-story houses. The entrance and exit were carried out through a checkpoint on Calabrian Street (former Apatit Street and another place to get to. Rakovskoy (former St. According to other sources, in Astrakhan.Romanovskaya Sloboda (former St.Republican). The territory of the ghetto was surrounded by barbed wire. There were security towers around the perimeter. The entire Jewish population was obliged to move to the ghetto within 5 days, because staying outside it was forbidden on pain of death. At the same time, residents of non-Jewish nationality had to leave the area. In November 1941, a part of the ghetto on Romanovskaya Sloboda, Kalvariyskaya, Sukhoi, Korona, Shornaya Streets stood out at probe No. 1. Between the streets of artisanal, Dimitrov, Oboyna, Rakovskaya, Nemiga, from 11/20/1941 to 07/28/1942, there was probe No. 2, where Jews deported from the Reich (Germany, Austria, Czech Republic, Poland, France and others). According to various estimates, there were at least 100 thousand prisoners in the Minsk ghetto. It was one of the largest ghettos in Europe and the second after Lviv on the territory of the former USSR. Ghetto residents had to constantly wear special identification signs: white stripes with house numbers on the chest and back and made of yellow ""star of David"" fabric. Living conditions in the ghetto were inhumane, large crowding (several families lived in one apartment, sometimes in one room), hunger, unsanitary conditions (lack of baths, electricity) led to outbreaks of diseases (furunculosis, scurvy, typhus and typhoid fever). 2 hospitals, a disabled and an orphanage were established in the ghetto. Working columns of Jews were taken out of the ghetto for forced hard labor. The use of Jewish labor took place in two forms: by hiring organizations, or by exploitation at subordinate enterprises. From November 1941, pogroms began in the ghetto. Only on November 7, 12 thousand people were killed. The pogrom was carried out on a strictly defined territory, between a part of Romanovskaya Sloboda Street (former Republican Street) and Rakovskaya (former Ostrovsky Street) and Nemiga and Khlebnaya Streets. They grabbed everyone except those who had a work ID. The next pogrom occurred on November 20, 1941, about 10 thousand people were killed. The mass punitive action took place on March 2, 1942. The Jewish Committee was given the task to prepare a column of 5,000 people, it seems, for the construction of the Stankovskaya railway line. Some of the prisoners died in the ghetto, some were taken out in the direction of D. Thrushes, part of them were sent to Koidanovo and shot there. Among those killed that day were 200 orphans from an orphanage along with staff. It is assumed that a total of about 6 thousand people died. The report of the security police and the SG dated March 9, 1942 stated that during the anti–Jewish action on March 2 - 3, 3412 Jews were shot in Minsk. On April 23, 1942, the Nazis staged a pogrom on Korolyov (shoe), Sukhoi, Saddlery and Collector Streets. About 500 people were killed. During the pogrom of July 28 – 31 , 1942 the Germans destroyed a hospital, a home for the disabled, another orphanage, people were taken to Trostenets. In four days, 10 thousand people were killed. In between the pogroms, raids, arrests, and shootings were carried out in the ghetto. Since the spring of 1942, people in the slaughterhouses were periodically taken to the Trostenets concentration camp. On October 21, 1943, the ghetto ceased to exist. The liquidation of the ghetto was carried out by the Minsk SG with the help of employees of the 26th police regiment, who arrived from Bialystok, and the 13th battalion of the SG. All Jews were taken to Trostenets or killed on the spot. Only 13 prisoners survived, who hid in an old crypt near the Jewish cemetery on Sukhoi. In 1947, an obelisk was erected at the intersection of Zaslavskaya and Melnikaite Streets in memory of 5,000 prisoners of the Minsk ghetto who were shot by the Nazis on March 2, 1942 (Authors Kamenyaches M. Sprishan and poet H. Maltinsky). It was the first monument to Jews in the USSR, in addition, the first monument on which it was allowed to make an inscription in Yiddish. The obelisk is installed at the bottom of the pit, where, according to the testimony of former prisoners, the bodies of the executed were dumped. It is not known exactly how many people were actually tortured here. The number of 5,000 people is indicated on the monument. Most likely, this is the total number of Jews killed that day. On March 2-3, prisoners from the ghetto were taken to other places for execution. According to V. Volozhinsky, about 500 corpses were dumped in it. In 2000, the sculptural composition ""the last way"" was installed in this place (authors A. Finsky, E. Pollak, L. Levin). It consists of asexual emaciated human figures descending in it. An alley of the ""Righteous of the Universe"" was planted near the memorial, 10 plaques with the names of Belarusian citizens who helped Jews escape during the war were placed near the trees. The memorial to the victims of the Nazi genocide is also known as the “Pit”. The monument was created for 8 years. All construction work on the construction of the memorial was carried out manually. Alexander Finsky is a well-known Belarusian sculptor working in the genre of easel, medal and monumental art. A. Finsky is the author of the monument to Simeon Polotsky in Polotsk, Adam Mickiewicz in Minsk, Maxim Tank in Myadel, the memorial complex “Red Coast” in the Gomel region, the “Zero Kilometer” sign on Oktyabrskaya Square in Minsk. Elsa Polak is an Israeli sculptor, a former prisoner of the Warsaw ghetto and ”Auschwitz"". Having no professional education, she sought to convey her experiences through creativity. Her works are in Yad Vashem, in the museum of Kibbutz Lohamei ha-Gettaot. Leonid Levin is an Honored architect of Belarus, laureate of the Lenin Prize and the Lenin Komsomol Prize, laureate of the Volgograd Komsomol Prize, twice laureate of the State Prize of the Republic of Belarus, laureate of numerous competitions, academician of the International and Belarusian Academy of Architecture. Born in Minsk. In 1960 graduated from the Belarusian Polytechnic Institute (now BNTU). He worked at the ”Minskproject"", since 1997 he was the head of his own creative workshop. Main works: memorial complexes “Khatyn"", “Pit” in Minsk, “breakthrough” (Ushachsky district), “the curse of fascism” (Shunevka village, Begomlsky district), a monument to Children who died in the Great Patriotic War in the town of Krasny Bereg (Zhlobinsky district), monuments to Ya. Kupala and Ya. Kolas in Minsk, to the victims of the Minsk ghetto on the Jubilee Square in Minsk, a memorial sign to the Jews shot in the town of Gorodey, the buildings of the City Committee of the CPB, VDNH (co-authored), etc."        </item>
        <item>"Concentration camp near d . Drozdy in the suburbs of Minsk is one of the first created by the Nazi invaders in Belarus. Most written sources report that the camp was founded by order of the commander of the 4th German Field Army, Field Marshal Kluke, in early July 1941 on the territory of the Krupskaya state farm. In the certificate prepared by the researcher of the Museum of the Great Patriotic War, N. A. Yatskevich in 1994, it is specified that the camp was established on June 30, 1941 and was considered as “Dulag No. 127”, that is, a transit camp. The area of the concentration camp was 9.3 hectares . It represented an open space surrounded by two rows of barbed wire, between which there was a 3 m wide stitch for the passage of guards. The camp was divided into six zones: ""senior commanders"", ""captured officers"", ""captured soldiers"", ""civilians of Minsk and the suburbs"", ""Jews"", ""persons with higher education"". All zones were divided among themselves by paths-passages 10-12 meters wide. On the north-eastern side of the camp there was a site for checking before being sent to the firing squad. The entrance to the camp was equipped from the northeast side of Nevavilonskaya Street. Mass executions took place 600-700 meters to the northeast of the camp. The conditions of the prisoners\' detention were inhumane. The ministerial adviser Drosh wrote in his note to Reichsleiter Rosenberg on 10.07.1941 that there were about 100 thousand people in the camp. prisoners of war and 40 thousand . civilians who are driven into a very tight area. They are almost unable to move and are forced to fulfill their natural needs where they stand. This camp, according to Dorsch, was guarded by only one company of soldiers, and its protection was possible only with the use of the toughest force. The issue of prisoners\' nutrition was not resolved, people lived for weeks without food, or rather, they ate only what citizens, residents of Minsk, who were not indifferent to their fate, passed on. The camp existed for several months, in August – September it was liquidated. The prisoners of war were transferred to other camps and the Minsk ghetto established in Minsk and the surrounding area. After the liberation of Belarus, the Extraordinary State Commission for the Identification and Investigation of Crimes of the Nazi invaders began its activities. She officially established the fact of the existence of a concentration camp near Minsk on Kaidasovaya Mountain, in the Drozdy tract. Exploring the site of the former camp at a distance of about 500 m to the northeast of it, a mass grave was discovered. According to an extract from the protocol drawn up on July 22, 1944, the remains of many corpses of tortured people were in a trench prepared for a water supply line in the pre-war period. According to eyewitnesses, prisoners from the camp shot by the Germans were buried here, as well as citizens brought from other places specially for this purpose. Among those killed were mostly political workers, commanders, employees of Soviet institutions, persons of Jewish nationality, as well as mentally ill people brought from the hospital in Novinki. Mass executions of prisoners of the camp took place here near the trench. In just a short period of existence of the concentration camp about d . More than 10 thousand people were tortured by thrushes.In the act of the Minsk regional Commission for the investigation of the crimes of the Nazi invaders dated August 13, 1944, the dimensions of the trench with the remains of dead people in the Drozdy tract are slightly larger - 400x2. 5x2. 5 m. the remains were found at a depth of 0.5 m from the Earth\'s surface. However, at that time, the burial place of prisoners was not memorialized. A poultry farm and military unit No. 22210-D were located on the territory of the former camp, and construction of garages began in the 1980s. Only after various earthworks in the area of the former concentration camp began to come across human skulls and bones, for the 50th anniversary of the Victory in front of the checkpoint of the military unit on Lenin Street. A monument was erected to Nevavilonskaya. Repeated work on the study of the burial of prisoners of the concentration camp “Drozdy” was carried out by the 52nd separate specialized search battalion of the Department for Perpetuating the Memory of Defenders of the Fatherland and Victims of Wars under the Ministry of Defense of the Republic of Belarus in 1996. During the search work, skeletons of men and women of different ages, the skeleton of a child (up to 10 years old) were revealed. Among the items there were fragments of women\'s shoes, bottles, coins, aluminum flasks, an officer\'s belt, fragments of a student card of the Gorky Minsk Pedagogical Institute and a reader\'s card of the Lenin Library, the newspaper ""Red Shift"" dated May 23, 1941. The found items belonged to both military and civilian citizens. Among the victims, the vast majority were prisoners of war and civilians of Minsk, there were border guards. Excavations have established the boundaries of the trench, which contained the remains of 10 thousand executed prisoners of war and civilians. The length of the trench was 305 m, width -3 m, depth – 0.9 – 1.7 m. the remains of the dead from excavations and pits were not destroyed. The boundaries of the burial were marked with temporary poles 1.1 m high along the entire length of the trench every 10 m . In 1997, a memorial stone was erected with the inscription ""Here in July 1941, the Nazi occupiers shot prisoners of the concentration camp ""Drozdy"": prisoners of war, civilians of Minsk and surrounding villages (about 10 thousand people). Posterity remembers you."" In 2009 the area around the memorial stone was landscaped: fenced, birch trees were planted, tiles were laid and a bench was put up."        </item>
        <item>"The years of occupation of Minsk by the Nazi invaders brought not only significant destruction, but also great human casualties. There were several places of mass destruction of prisoners of war and civilians in Minsk and its environs. One of these places was in the area of the former d . Uruchye is on the northeastern outskirts of the city. Here, on the 9th km along the Minsk-Moscow highway, 800 m from the highway and 250 m from the road to Zaslavl, 10 pit graves were found (in the cornice-swamp tract). The dimensions of eight graves were 21x5 m, one – 20x6 m, the depth was 3-5 m. The Minsk Regional Commission for Assistance in the work of the Extraordinary State Commission for the Identification and Investigation of Crimes of the Nazi Invaders has uncovered a pit grave, in which 3 longitudinal rows of corpses in 7 layers each were found. All the corpses were lying face down, they were wearing military and civilian-style clothing and shoes. Among the dead prisoners of war there were many in the form of tank troops. Documents, watches, government bonds, Soviet money and various personal items were found in the pockets of the clothes of some corpses. The prevailing age of the victims is 20-30 years. There were also several corpses of women in civilian clothes in the grave. Grave graves and in the graves found a large number of spent cartridges from German rifle cartridges. During the forensic examination of 120 corpses exhumed from this grave, it was found that the cause of death of the deceased in all cases were through-through gunshot bullet wounds to the head, accompanied by significant damage to the bones of the vault and the base of the skull. All this testifies to the shooting of prisoners of war with rifles or carbines from very close distances. The total number of people shot and buried on the territory of the cornice swamp, according to the testimony of witnesses and examination data, exceeds 30 thousand people. In accordance with the Resolution of the BSSR Council of Ministers of April 16, 1956 No. 202, the BSSR State Construction Committee ordered Belgosproekt to develop monuments on the graves of mass graves of soldiers of the Soviet Army, partisans and civilians who died in the Great Patriotic War. Before June 1, 1956, it was necessary to submit sketches of monuments. Therefore, at the first stage, a design assignment of standard monuments for mass graves was developed. Architects G. Benediktov and A. Dukhan worked on the project assignment. They performed three versions of the monuments, and the composition of all three variants is designed for a four-sided perception of the monument. Option 1. was a truncated pyramidal tombstone with memorial plaques on each side, placed on a gentle four-sided bully mound, bounded on a square base by a side. The tombstone, memorial plaques and sideboard were made of concrete slabs, textured with granite chips. Option 2. the monument is designed in the form of an obelisk with a small base, also placed on a small square mound with a concrete side. Memorial plaques are placed on the sides of the mound. In the lower third of the obelisk, cast-iron emblems are embedded on four sides. The obelisk, memorial plaques and the side are concrete, shaped like granite. Option 3. A monument in the form of a slightly modified obelisk on the same basis as option 2, with the same memorial plaques. Cast iron wreaths are located on 4 sides. These developments served as the basis for further design of monuments at the place of mass burial of Soviet soldiers and civilians in the village of Masyukovshchina, Trostenets, Uruchye. The project of the monument in the area of Uruchye was performed in 1956 by V. Volchek. Viktor Matveyevich Volchek (1910 – 1985) was a Belarusian architect and teacher, Honored Architect of Belarus (1978). Graduated from the Leningrad Academy of Arts (1936). Since 1953 he worked in Minsk. His main works in Belarus: the building of the Minsk Regional Executive Committee (1958), the building of the Ya. Kupala Literary Museum (1959), a residential building on K. Marx Street (1959), a monument to F. E. Dzerzhinsky (1953, sculptor Z. Azgur), M. Kazeyu (1958, sculptor S. Selikhanov), monuments to V. I. Lenin in Mogilev (1958, sculptor P. Sabsay) and Molodechno (1959, sculptor Z. Azgur), the victims of the death camp in Masyukovshchina (1959), the soldiers of the Polish division named after T. Kosciusko in the village of Lenin, Goretsky district (1953), an obelisk in honor of Soviet soldiers and partisans in the town of Ivanets, Volozhinsky district (1959, sculptor Ya. Pechkin). One of the authors of the Brest Fortress memorial complex is a hero. From the explanatory note to the monument project on the 9th km of the Moscow highway, it followed that in the valley of Uruchye contains mass graves of prisoners of war of Soviet soldiers and partisans in the amount of 30,000. The graves are located all over the valley, it is impossible to combine them into one fraternal cemetery. Therefore, the author chose a place for the memorial, taking into account the topographic features, so that the monument was clearly visible from distant points of the Moscow highway. For these reasons, the top of the hill bordering the valley was chosen for the monument. The hill is crossed by a highway, on the south side of the highway there is a military school. At the same time, it was noted that the stalls in front of the school were organically a continuation of the stalls in front of the monument. According to the author, the chosen site created favorable conditions for approaching the monument during the celebrations. A small number of remains of soldiers and civilians killed by the Nazi occupiers were transferred and reburied to the monument under construction. An asphalt parking area with a width of 8 m and a length of 40 m was designed next to the memorial. The staircase with a slope of 1: 3 and a width of 27 m was designed from precast reinforced concrete slabs treated for buchard. According to the project, the paths of the upper terrace were covered with a 10 cm brick battle and sprinkled with white sand. All the boundaries of the plot and flower beds were framed by a border. On the outer sides of the plot, planting of high-crowned trees was envisaged. It was planned to plant Crimean silver firs along the axis of the flower garden. On the sidewalks it was supposed to install benches for recreation, which were made of the same material as the monument. The composition of the monument was designed to be perceived from distant points of the Moscow highway. The obelisk was designed with a height of 17 m and had an isosceles trapezoid in plan. An inscription about the events to which the monument is dedicated should be placed on the front face. On the sides of the obelisk there are bent foliage, between them a wreath and a helmet.The foundation of the monument was designed from rubble concrete, the backbone is hollow, made of monolithic reinforced concrete with plastered natural granite. The inscriptions were recommended to be executed in plaster. To do this, the letters from the drywall had to be inserted in the same plane with the plaster. When the plaster dried, the plaster letters were taken out, after which there was an imprint of the text. Banners, wreaths and a helmet were cast from cast iron. V. Volchek executed two versions of the monument, which differed slightly. A project was implemented according to which the obelisk is rectangular in plan on a smaller pedestal. On the side wings there are bent flags, and on the obelisk itself there is a wreath and the date ""1941-1945"". The construction of the monument was completed in 1959. In 1958, the General Directorate for Architecture commissioned Belgosproekt to develop a project for the layout, fencing and landscaping of the Fraternal Cemetery. According to the project (author V. Volchek) it was envisaged to take an area of 1.5 hectares behind the obelisk for the fraternal cemetery, where the remains of prisoners of war, partisans and civilians killed by the Nazi invaders were reburied from graves scattered in the valley and near the cornice swamp. Alleys were planned on the territory of the Fraternal Cemetery, graves were recommended to be edged with turf and curbstone, flower beds and planting of ornamental shrubs were organized, three sculptures were installed, a ceramic fence with a height of 1.8 m was erected along the perimeter. This project has not been implemented. The cemetery has not been made from the rear of the monument. Now behind the monument is a hillside overgrown with trees. According to researcher A. I.Usachev, the mass graves in which the executed prisoners of war and civilians are buried are located on the right side of the road to Zaslavl, in the area of the cornice swamp, on the edge of the current shooting range and near the former village. Uruchye."        </item>
        <item>"The military cemetery of Minsk, along with the Kalvari Cemetery, is one of the oldest necropolises in the city, where many outstanding people of Belarus are buried.The beginning of the formation of the military cemetery in Minsk dates back to the 1840s. The exact date of the cemetery\'s foundation is not indicated in written sources. It is known from archival documents that the cemetery was founded at a military hospital.They were located in the forest of the bishop\'s estate, called Antonov. At that time, this territory was outside the city limits. It should be noted that according to the project plan of Minsk in 1858 Also, it was not supposed to include this territory in the boundaries of the city, the cemetery is not indicated on it. The military hospital was located in a block near the city border.In 1850, the territory of the cemetery of the Minsk Military Hospital was expanded at the expense of 1 tithe of land leased from landowner Eduard Stanislavovich Vankovich (1.0925 hectares). The contract for the lease of a plot of land was signed by the Minsk City Administration with E. Vankovich on June 5 , 1850 . In this regard, the office of the military hospital demanded that the Minsk City administration ""enclose with a fence or dig in ditches both the land currently allocated and previously occupied for the cemetery"" at the expense of the city. However, the city authorities considered that this was not their responsibility. The issue of fencing was even considered at a meeting of the Minsk provincial government in 1851, at which it was recommended that the office of the military hospital contact the military department, since the hospital and cemetery existed at the expense of this department.The issue of expanding the territory of the cemetery arose more acutely in the early 1880s. For 40 years of the hospital\'s existence, the cemetery territory, which occupied an area of 1 tithe, was overflowing with burials. According to the study by the city surveyor of the area where the cemetery is located, it turned out that there was no urban land near the cemetery. Then, the military hospital proposed to allocate a plot of city land for a hospital cemetery in another place, and close the old cemetery. The city council offered the hospital a free piece of city land for perespeya (Storozhevik district). But the military department was not satisfied with this option. After all, this place was located behind the shooting range, more than 3 versts from the hospital, besides, the terrain was low-lying and swampy, which in no way suited the placement of a cemetery here. For this reason, the Minsk Military Hospital rejected this offer, and the city authorities had no other vacant plots suitable for a cemetery. The correspondence dragged on for a year. Then the leadership of the military hospital turned to the Minsk civil governor for assistance, who instructed the city administration to re-enter into negotiations with the owner of the land adjacent to the cemetery, landowner Vankovich. The landowner Vankovich, the owner of the Slepyanka estate, again agreed to give up one tithe of the adjacent land for an annual rent for the expansion of the hospital cemetery, but on condition that the petty bourgeois Rodevich, who took this tithe of land for rent in 1879 under a contract for 12 years, agrees to terminate the terms of the contract ahead of time. A long correspondence between the city administration and the Duma and the military department on the issue of monetary compensation to Rodevich and rent to Vankovich began again. The commander of the troops of the Vilna military District did not recognize it possible to acquire land for a cemetery at the expense of the treasury. The City Duma, given the insignificance of city funds, also did not want to burden the city with these expenses. As a result, at a meeting on April 2, 1884, the City Duma rejected the request of the military hospital to expand the territory of the cemetery. In 1890, the Minsk City Council was contacted by the chief of staff of the district again on the issue of expanding the territory of the cemetery. It was reported that several rooms had to be buried in one grave. Perhaps the appeal of the chiefs of staff somehow accelerated the matter. And on July 13, 1891, Rodevich gave a receipt that for 250 rubles. he agrees to assign his rights to the land to the city. And on October 16, 1891, Yan Sigismundovich Vankovich notarized that he was giving land in the suburb of Long Ford of the Minsk City Council for a period of 1891-1903 for 12-year lease maintenance. Thus, once again the territory of the cemetery was increased by more than a tithe of the land leased from Vankovich from the Slepyanka estate. In 1896-98 at the military cemetery designed by the Minsk diocesan architect V. I. Russian Russian troops in the Russo-Turkish War of 1877-78, the Alexander Nevsky Church was built in honor of the victory of the Russian troops in the 1877-78 war, which has been preserved and operates to this day. It is a cross-domed three-nave one-apse four-pillar church. In the center of the symmetrical three-dimensional composition stands a massive dome on an octagonal light drum, completed with a bulbous dome. Smaller domes are symmetrically located above the side naves. The dominant feature of the composition is a high two-tiered bell tower with a tent covering, located above the narthex and designed in the same style with the architecture of the temple. The rich plasticity of the facades of the church is given by numerous arcature belts, complex multi-layered arches over window and door openings, rosettes, ornamental frieze, complexly profiled gzims, columns. The captivating space is bounded by four pillars complex in cross-section and connected to the side aisles by arched openings. The altar part is separated from the main room, rises three steps in a semicircular outline. In the vestibule at the entrance to the central nave on the inner walls there are memorial plaques with the names of Belarusian soldiers of the 30th Artillery Brigade and the 119th Kolomna Regiment, who heroically died near Plevna. Military relics are kept in the temple: a field church and regimental banners. Officers were buried behind the altar wall of the church, and soldiers were buried a little further away in two mass graves. In 1903, a new petition of the military hospital was followed for cutting to the military cemetery from the back of the land belonging to the landowner Vankovich and being in rent maintenance from Bartashevich. Unfortunately, it is not known whether this petition was granted and the cemetery area was increased. Probably, the issue was not resolved positively, and soon the cemetery was closed. So on the plan of Minsk 1905, the cemetery of the military hospital in the explication to the plan is marked ""abolished"". Judging by the plan, by this time, 1st Dolgobrodskaya Street (the site of modern Kozlov Street) and Vyuga Street (modern street) had already been laid near the military cemetery. Smolyachkova). However, the area around the cemetery is not yet divided into blocks. By the beginning of the 1910s, as evidenced by the plan of Since 1911, the situation around the military cemetery has changed to a certain extent. By this time, new streets had already appeared, which divided the area into blocks. Thus, the block that included the Military Cemetery was limited to Dolgobrodskaya, Yamnaya (modern Mikhailovskaya Street), Zolotogorskaya (modern Krasnoznamennaya Street) and Berestyanskaya streets. In the 1920s and 1930s, famous party, military, scientific figures, representatives of the creative intelligentsia were buried at the Military Cemetery. 8 Red partisans who died in 1919-20 are buried in mass graves. Grave graves After the Great Patriotic War, the remains of the participants of the Minsk underground were reburied in the Military Cemetery in mass graves, 4 soldiers who died during the liberation of Minsk were buried in other mass graves. In addition, 42 mass graves and more than 500 individual graves were organized in the northwestern part of the cemetery from Kozlov St., in which more than 1,000 soldiers who died in battles with the Nazi invaders were buried. In 1965, a monument-sculpture of a warrior was erected at the fraternal cemetery, tombstones were made on fraternal and single graves. In 1948 a new fence was designed around the military cemetery. The author of the project is architect I. Rudenko. The project provided for the fencing of the Military Cemetery from four sides with a total length of about 800 m. from Lenin Street. Berestyanskaya, Krasnozdnaya and Yamnaya (modern Mikhailovskaya St.), according to the order of the City Executive Committee, the fence is designed according to the type of fencing of the park. Chelyuskintsev, with a span of a link in the axes of the pillars in 3.33 m to 3.27 m and with some change in the top of the pillars. Gates with a width of 1.20 m are provided along Berestyanskaya and Krasnozdnaya Streets . Fence from the side of the street . Dolgobrodskaya (modern Kozlov Street) is designed with a new version. The span between the pillars was made at 3.58 m, the height of the fence is 2.22 m. At the location of the old gate, the main entrance to the cemetery was preserved and an additional gate with a span of 3.55 m to the territory of the recent burial was designed not far from it. The main entrance was solved in the plan by a courier with an indentation deep into the cemetery from the red line by one link. The transition from a light fence to a massive three-span architrave gate is secured by two flanking steles. The filling of the fence was provided for metal from a rod with a diameter of 19 m through 0.15 m . The pillars of the spans and gates according to the project were recommended to be made of brick, the foundations of brick rubble. All the fence posts, the Stella and the gate were supposed to be plastered in a fur coat. Traction is performed with smooth plaster, followed by painting with cement milk with the addition of earthen dye. In the tone of the current, it was recommended to process the modeling. It was recommended to paint the metal part of the fence with black oil paint. In the post - war period , the national poets of Belarus Ya were buried in the Military Cemetery . Kupala and Ya. Kolas, Ya. Kupala\'s mother B. I. Lutsevich and wife V. F. Lutsevich, Ya. Kolas\' wife M. D. Mitskevich, Heroes of the Soviet Union B. S. Akrestin, A.V. Akhmanov, B. A. Mikhailov, A.M. Rabtsevich, S. I. Sikorsky, E. F. Filipskikh, N. Ya. Chibisov, A.M. Yurin, folk artists A. D. Arsenko, G. Y. Grigonis, famous Soviet architect A. P. Bregman, writers M. Klimkovich and K. Cherny, poet V. Tavlay, playwright E. A. Mirovich, composers N.F. Sokolovsky, A. E. Turankov, statesman I.D."        </item>
        <item>"The fraternal cemetery in Minsk was created at the request of the Alexander Committee. Information about the history of the cemetery\'s foundation is contained in an archival document from the funds of the National Historical Archive of Belarus ""the case of the Minsk City Administration on the establishment of a Fraternal cemetery in the city of Minsk for the burial of soldiers-victims of the Great European War"" for 1914-1915. It is proposed to build boards with the names of fallen soldiers in all parish churches; in addition, in the homeland of the murdered, monuments of at least primitive devices in the form of chapels, crosses, stone pillars, slabs and the like should be erected in more prominent places. In the care of perpetuating the memory of the victims of the real war, the Alexander Committee for the Wounded plunged into the Highest benevolence of the desire that dying soldiers should be buried in each city only in a certain cemetery and in one place. Subsequently, such cemeteries can be planted with trees, surrounded by a lattice and will represent special fraternal cemeteries. They can be used to build chapels, crosses, monuments, etc. Such fraternal cemeteries will remind future generations of the Victims of the Great European War"""" These proposals were supported by the head of the Minsk Military District Administration. October 30 , 1914 at a joint meeting of representatives of the city and zemstvo authorities of the Minsk province, a resolution was adopted on the speedy implementation of the proposals of the Alexander Committee, and on November 3, the Minsk City Duma at its meeting considered the issue ""on the arrangement of mass graves and cemeteries"" and decided: ""To instruct the city council to purchase one dozen of land at the Vilna Tract from the Clergy of the Minsk Cathedral for the construction of a separate fraternal cemetery."" At the same time, the Minsk provincial government, ""recognizing the one-tenth plot of land allocated by the city of Minsk between the Vilensky and Dolgovsky tracts for the fraternal cemetery,"" on November 29 gave permission to open this cemetery and commissioned the construction of an Orthodox chapel there. At the end of 1914, the territory of the cemetery was surrounded by a wooden fence with a gate. On November 17, 1914, the Minsk City Duma approved the project and estimate for the construction of a cemetery and an Orthodox chapel developed by the Minsk city architect F. Zholandkovsky. At the same time, work continued on the improvement of the cemetery - their territory was divided into special squares, paths were laid. The landscaping work was completed in May 1915. The chapel began to be built in the spring of 1915, and very soon the temple was erected. The official documents note that the military cemetery was directly subordinate to the Minsk military commandant and had the official name ""Minsk Fraternal Military Cemetery. Burials in the cemetery were carried out until 1918, and according to some sources – until 1920. they existed until the Second World War. They were indicated on the German plan of Minsk in 1942. During the occupation of Minsk, the Nazi invaders founded a death camp for prisoners of war and civilians on the territory of the cemetery from July 1, 1941. The territory was surrounded by barbed wire. The prisoners were kept in the open air. The deceased were buried 50 m from the camp, on the side of Chervyakova Street. In 2010, the landscaping works were completed. Based on the materials of V. Denisov \'s research"        </item>

        <item>"Kupala Park was founded in 1949 on the banks of the Svisloch River as a park named after the 30th anniversary of the BSSR. There was a residential quarter on the site of the park before the Great Patriotic War. The building of the quarter was mostly wooden. During the bombing, residential buildings were destroyed. In 1949, a park was laid out on the ashes, more than 4 thousand trees were planted, alleys were laid. The author of the park project is architect I. Rudenko. The main alley of the park ran diagonally from the entrance from the avenue to the bend of the Svisloch. A monument to pilot S. I. Gritsevets, the first Hero of the Soviet Union twice, was erected on it. Further, in the center of the stalls, in the middle of a large round flowerbed, a sculptural composition on the theme of peaceful life was placed. Years later, this composition will be dismantled and, according to the project of architect V. Martyanov, a fountain was made in 1958. In 1954 and 1955, a project was developed for an architecturally decorated main entrance to the park (architect Belousov) and a balustrade on the side of the avenue (architect G. Badanov, M. Parashnikov). In 1959, the Yanka Kupala Literary Museum (architect I. Volodko, V. Volchek) was built in the park on the site where the house where the national poet lived in 1927-1941 stood. In 1962 By the 80th anniversary of the birth of Yanka Kupala, the park was renamed in his honor. In 1972, the park was reconstructed for the poet\'s 90th anniversary. A monument to Yanka Kupala was erected on the central alley of the park (sculptors A. Anikeychik, L. Gumilevsky, A. Zaspitsky, architect Y. Gradov, L. Levin). The fountain was also rebuilt. The new composition of the fountain was called ""wreath"". It reflects one of the moments of the ancient folk holiday-Kupala. In 2007-2009, project documentation was developed and work is underway on the reconstruction and improvement of the Ya Park. Kupala (reconstruction of the pavement of paths, curbs, outdoor lighting, fountain, benches, partial change of layout, etc.)."        </item>
        <item>"The Loshitsa estate has been mentioned in written sources since the 16th century . In the documents of the Lithuanian Metric for 1557, the ""Loshitsky Courtyard"" of Prince Tolochinsky and the ""Dry Loshitsa Courtyard of Prince Odintsovo"" are called"" In the Acts of the Minsk City Court for 1582-1590, the Loshitsa estate is listed as Gornostaevskaya or Bolshaya. It is known that later these estates passed into the possession of the princes of Drutsky-Gorsky. In 1597 there was a division of the Loshitsky estate between the princes of Drutsky-Gorsky: “...To Prince Fyodor Gorsky, the Loshitsa of Gornostaevskaya and Samuel, Konstantin and Simeon Piotrovich Princes of Drutsky-Gorsky, appointing the Loshitsa of Odintsovo and at the same time delimiting Loshitsy among themselves...” Thus, the estate of Loshitsa Gornostaevskaya, which has survived to our time, in 1597 became owned by Prince Fyodor of Drutsky-Gorsky. After his death in 1615, his son Grigory owned the estate. In 1659 Loshitsa was inherited by Gregory Theodore\'s son, the king, the next owner was Theodore\'s youngest son, Mikhailantony Gorsky. The Gorskys owned Loshitsa until the beginning of the 18th century . According to a document discovered in the funds of the National Historical Archive by V. Denisov, on April 16, 1719, the Gorskys issued the right to sell “a well-Loshitsa with all, Obchak and Koledichi, called, located in the Minsk voivodeship... together with the eternal possession of the same Lochitsa estate ... their bridges to Jerzy Antony and Teresa Prushinsky."" However, according to the second document, Jerzy Prushinsky acquired the estate back in 1703. after him, the Loshitsa was owned by his son Jozef Pruszynski, a sub-commander of the Minsk voivodeship, a knight of the Order of St. Stanislaus. His name is associated with the formation of the Baroque manor of the second half of the 18th century. In 1779, all the possessions of Jozef Prushinsky were divided among the children: Ignatius, Anton, Fadey, Felician, Stanislav, Casimir, Anna, Francisca, Felicianna, Justina. The Loshitsky estate went to Kazimir. Soon he died and his part of the parental legacy passed to his brother Stanislav, who owned the estate of Korolishchevichi in the Igumen district. In 1789, as the document testifies, ""the Loshitsa estate in the Minsk voivodeship with the villages: Loshitsa, Kolyadichi and Opchaki, with all the manor buildings, fields, meadows, forests, forests, dams, taverns, mills..."" Stanislav Prushinsky assigned to his brother Anthony. According to the will drawn up in 1806 and certified in 1813, Stanislav-Xavier, the son of Anthony, left his lands to his wife Anna. Anna Prushinskaya died in 1820. In turn, she bequeathed the property to her children: three sons and a daughter. After the death of the eldest son Karl, the heirs were Eustathius, Prot and Stanislava, by her husband Lyubanskaya. Then in 1825, Proto Prushinsky gave up his part of the estate in favor of his brother Evstafy. In the reference edition” Lists of landowners of the Minsk province for 1876. "" it is reported that Evstafy Prushinsky was the sole owner of the Loshitsa since 1822. Evstafy Prushinsky had no direct heirs and after his death the estate passed through the female line to the son of Stanislava\'s sister ona Lubansky. In 1884, Ya. Lyubansky died, leaving the Loshitsa to his wife Alexandra Osipovna Lyubanskaya for life, then inherited in 1885. the estate passed into possession in equal parts to the sons of Evstafy and Alexander Lyubansky. Evstafiy Lyubansky is associated with the period of the most successful development of the Loshitsa estate, which became one of the best provincial farms, and Loshitsa became a famous place of social life. Evstafiy knew agriculture well, was a member of the Minsk Agricultural Society, chairman of the committee of the Minsk Forest Exchange, was elected to the city and State Duma of the first convocation. In 1889, Yevstafiy Lubansky married Jadwiga Kenevich. According to the memoirs of her brother Anthony Kenevich, ""a few years after the marriage, Evstafia Loshitsa became a manor with high culture, with a modernized brewery and a large rectification ...” In 1905, Jadwiga tragically died, Evstafia left for the Caucasus, where he died soon after. The last owners of the Loshitsa estate were Evstafia\'s brother Alexander from Lyuban and their sister. After the revolution, the estate entered the knowledge of the State Political Administration. For a while there was an orphanage here. On September 1, 1920, it was transferred to the order of the Beijing University Commission for the Agronomic State University. Since 1925, the Belarusian branch of the All-Union Institute of Plant Growing has been located in Loshitsa. M. I. Vavilov came here on September 15, 1928. Later, Loshitsa belonged to the Institute of Agriculture. During the German occupation, the German headquarters was located in the manor house and the Minsk underground almost destroyed it. V. Loshitsa is included within the limits of Minsk according to the Decree of the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of the BSSR dated 30.08.1985 No. 327-Xi.The earliest inventory of the Loshitsa estate dates back to 1772 . It can be used to reconstruct the estate at the end of the 18th – beginning of the 19th century . The description of the Loshitsa Gornostaevskaya estate begins from the Minsk – Igumen road, on which the tavern stood. To the right of the inn there was a pond, to the left there was a dam and a mill with 2 wheels. Nearby there was a brewery with a complex of outbuildings. There was also a barnyard. The economic zone was surrounded by a fence. There was a bridge over the dam, and behind it ” on the mountain"" there was a manor house on a stone foundation, a stable, behind them below – a gate with a gate that faced the old Minsk hotel. Along the entrance alley, as in many manors of that time, there were gardens. In the inventory, the manor house is described in some detail: ""... large on the foundation, covered with shingles, a porch in front of the house, double doors in the canopy of carpentry, on hinges with a latch with a latch, holes and hooks... There are two round windows in the vestibule, one glazed, framed in tin, from the vestibule on the right hand there is the first room with double doors of carpentry on hinges with a latch... In the same room there are tin framed windows... four, glazed coffee tile stove, with fireplace, from that room the door to the other room is double joinery, on hinges... in the same room there is one window on hinges with hooks and holes, an oven made of green tile, with a fireplace and a bakery stove, from that room going to the bedroom door on hinges... in that room there are two windows framed in tin, with hinges... From that room to the wardrobe , the door is on hinges with a latch ... there are two windows there... with a collar. Returning through the bedroom, from another room the door to the hall is double, carpentry work without retouching. In that hall there are three windows without frames and glass, from that hall to the side room there are double doors of carpentry... one window, a green tile stove with a fireplace and a baker\'s stove, from that room to the room... doors, three windows in it framed in tin... from that room to the cloakroom there is a door on hinges with an internal lock... where akon is two; returning to the mentioned room, the door to the room is the first, double on hinges... with an iron handle and an internal lock, there are four windows in the same room... glazed tile oven with a plate, a sideboard of painted carpentry... the door to the basement is on hinges with a hook and holes, in the middle... there are four drawers in it. The lid is on hinges. The closet is on top... with shelves, double hinged doors, with an internal lock. From that room in the vestibule there are double doors of carpentry, on hinges with a latch...There are three chimneys from that building to the roof, three stone basements under the same house, five windows with iron bars in them, doors on hinges with latches and breakdowns, internal locks in three doors, with a Kralevsky padlock in the fourth."" ""The floor and ceiling in all the rooms were made of boards, well planed"""" The next inventory of the estate dates back to 1789. Judging by the description of the house, there were no changes in its planning structure. However, it contains very important information. Thus, when describing the last living room, the inscription in Polish ”Roku Tysiąc Siedemset Dwadziestego Czwartego"" is mentioned on the support beam. This dating may indicate that in 1724 the building was built or substantially rebuilt. In addition to the above - mentioned inventory , the Lviv Scientific Library named after V. Stefanik has a watercolor by Yu . peshka of the early 19th century . (no later than 1810), on which the entire estate is represented. The center of the composition was the described wooden house. It was rectangular in plan and covered with a high hip roof. Not far from the house there are one-storey buildings of an economic complex. In the foreground there is a tavern and a mill on the stave, then a chapel behind the stave. In the 19th century. the estate has been reconstructed. Exact information about the time of perestroika has not been found in written sources, but, most likely, according to researchers V. Denisov, V. Kukuni, the reconstruction was carried out by Evstafy Ivanovich Prushinsky in the early 1880s, no later than 1883 A. T. Fedoruk attributes the reconstruction of the estate to 1890-1895. The estate was surrounded by a metal wrought-iron fence. A well-maintained park, a new front entrance to the manor house was made along a wide linden alley from the north-west side. The layout of the park has lost its regularity, but its general features have not changed. Landscape compositions were formed in place of the baskets. A manor house, an outbuilding, was built, more precisely, rebuilt, old outbuildings were demolished, a new economic yard was created, and an industrial complex appeared on the site of the old one. As a result of the reconstruction, the manor house received an asymmetric three-dimensional copposition. To the north-eastern facade of an old wooden house of the early 18th century. a stone two-storey volume was added. The new stone volume was covered with a four-pitched roof with a cornice of considerable removal. The risalits under the gable roofs are completed with triangular pediments decorated with invalid half-timbered windows. The reconstruction of the old part of the building was carried out extremely organically. Wooden carved details are widely used in the architectural design of facades: window frames, pediments, listening windows. The main entrance is highlighted by an original portico, the visor of which was supported by carved wooden columns on a high plinth."        </item>
        <item>"The Loshitsa estate has been mentioned in written sources since the 16th century . In the documents of the Lithuanian Metric for 1557, the ""Loshitsky Courtyard"" of Prince Tolochinsky and the ""Dry Loshitsa Courtyard of Prince Odintsovo"" are called"" In the Acts of the Minsk City Court for 1582-1590, the Loshitsa estate is listed as Gornostaevskaya or Bolshaya. It is known that later these estates passed into the possession of the princes of Drutsky-Gorsky. In 1597 there was a division of the Loshitsky estate between the princes of Drutsky-Gorsky: “...To Prince Fyodor Gorsky, the Loshitsa of Gornostaevskaya and Samuel, Konstantin and Simeon Piotrovich Princes of Drutsky-Gorsky, appointing the Loshitsa of Odintsovo and at the same time delimiting Loshitsy among themselves...” Thus, the estate of Loshitsa Gornostaevskaya, which has survived to our time, in 1597 became owned by Prince Fyodor of Drutsky-Gorsky. After his death in 1615, his son Grigory owned the estate. In 1659 Loshitsa was inherited by Gregory Theodore\'s son, the king, the next owner was Theodore\'s youngest son, Mikhailantony Gorsky. The Gorskys owned Loshitsa until the beginning of the 18th century . According to a document discovered in the funds of the National Historical Archive by V. Denisov, on April 16, 1719, the Gorskys issued the right to sell “a well-Loshitsa with all, Obchak and Koledichi, called, located in the Minsk voivodeship... together with the eternal possession of the same Lochitsa estate ... their bridges to Jerzy Antony and Teresa Prushinsky."" However, according to the second document, Jerzy Prushinsky acquired the estate back in 1703. after him, the Loshitsa was owned by his son Jozef Pruszynski, a sub-commander of the Minsk voivodeship, a knight of the Order of St. Stanislaus. His name is associated with the formation of the Baroque manor of the second half of the 18th century. In 1779, all the possessions of Jozef Prushinsky were divided among the children: Ignatius, Anton, Fadey, Felician, Stanislav, Casimir, Anna, Francisca, Felicianna, Justina. The Loshitsky estate went to Kazimir. Soon he died and his part of the parental legacy passed to his brother Stanislav, who owned the estate of Korolishchevichi in the Igumen district. In 1789, as the document testifies, ""the Loshitsa estate in the Minsk voivodeship with the villages: Loshitsa, Kolyadichi and Opchaki, with all the manor buildings, fields, meadows, forests, forests, dams, taverns, mills..."" Stanislav Prushinsky assigned to his brother Anthony. According to the will drawn up in 1806 and certified in 1813, Stanislav-Xavier, the son of Anthony, left his lands to his wife Anna. Anna Prushinskaya died in 1820. In turn, she bequeathed the property to her children: three sons and a daughter. After the death of the eldest son Karl, the heirs were Eustathius, Prot and Stanislava, by her husband Lyubanskaya. Then in 1825, Proto Prushinsky gave up his part of the estate in favor of his brother Evstafy. In the reference edition” Lists of landowners of the Minsk province for 1876. "" it is reported that Evstafy Prushinsky was the sole owner of the Loshitsa since 1822. Evstafy Prushinsky had no direct heirs and after his death the estate passed through the female line to the son of Stanislava\'s sister ona Lubansky. In 1884, Ya. Lyubansky died, leaving the Loshitsa to his wife Alexandra Osipovna Lyubanskaya for life, then inherited in 1885. the estate passed into possession in equal parts to the sons of Evstafy and Alexander Lyubansky. Evstafiy Lyubansky is associated with the period of the most successful development of the Loshitsa estate, which became one of the best provincial farms, and Loshitsa became a famous place of social life. Evstafiy knew agriculture well, was a member of the Minsk Agricultural Society, chairman of the committee of the Minsk Forest Exchange, was elected to the city and State Duma of the first convocation. In 1889, Yevstafiy Lubansky married Jadwiga Kenevich. According to the memoirs of her brother Anthony Kenevich, ""a few years after the marriage, Evstafia Loshitsa became a manor with high culture, with a modernized brewery and a large rectification ...” In 1905, Jadwiga tragically died, Evstafia left for the Caucasus, where he died soon after. The last owners of the Loshitsa estate were Evstafia\'s brother Alexander from Lyuban and their sister. After the revolution, the estate entered the knowledge of the State Political Administration. For a while there was an orphanage here. On September 1, 1920, it was transferred to the order of the Beijing University Commission for the Agronomic State University. Since 1925, the Belarusian branch of the All-Union Institute of Plant Growing has been located in Loshitsa. M. I. Vavilov came here on September 15, 1928. Later, Loshitsa belonged to the Institute of Agriculture. During the German occupation, the German headquarters was located in the manor house and the Minsk underground almost destroyed it. V. Loshitsa is included within the limits of Minsk according to the Decree of the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of the BSSR dated 30.08.1985 No. 327-Xi.The earliest inventory of the Loshitsa estate dates back to 1772 . It can be used to reconstruct the estate at the end of the 18th – beginning of the 19th century . The description of the Loshitsa Gornostaevskaya estate begins from the Minsk – Igumen road, on which the tavern stood. To the right of the inn there was a pond, to the left there was a dam and a mill with 2 wheels. Nearby there was a brewery with a complex of outbuildings. There was also a barnyard. The economic zone was surrounded by a fence. There was a bridge over the dam, and behind it ” on the mountain"" there was a manor house on a stone foundation, a stable, behind them below – a gate with a gate that faced the old Minsk hotel. Along the entrance alley, as in many manors of that time, there were gardens. In the inventory, the manor house is described in some detail: ""... large on the foundation, covered with shingles, a porch in front of the house, double doors in the canopy of carpentry, on hinges with a latch with a latch, holes and hooks... There are two round windows in the vestibule, one glazed, framed in tin, from the vestibule on the right hand there is the first room with double doors of carpentry on hinges with a latch... In the same room there are tin framed windows... four, glazed coffee tile stove, with fireplace, from that room the door to the other room is double joinery, on hinges... in the same room there is one window on hinges with hooks and holes, an oven made of green tile, with a fireplace and a bakery stove, from that room going to the bedroom door on hinges... in that room there are two windows framed in tin, with hinges... From that room to the wardrobe , the door is on hinges with a latch ... there are two windows there... with a collar. Returning through the bedroom, from another room the door to the hall is double, carpentry work without retouching. In that hall there are three windows without frames and glass, from that hall to the side room there are double doors of carpentry... one window, a green tile stove with a fireplace and a baker\'s stove, from that room to the room... doors, three windows in it framed in tin... from that room to the cloakroom there is a door on hinges with an internal lock... where akon is two; returning to the mentioned room, the door to the room is the first, double on hinges... with an iron handle and an internal lock, there are four windows in the same room... glazed tile oven with a plate, a sideboard of painted carpentry... the door to the basement is on hinges with a hook and holes, in the middle... there are four drawers in it. The lid is on hinges. The closet is on top... with shelves, double hinged doors, with an internal lock. From that room in the vestibule there are double doors of carpentry, on hinges with a latch...There are three chimneys from that building to the roof, three stone basements under the same house, five windows with iron bars in them, doors on hinges with latches and breakdowns, internal locks in three doors, with a Kralevsky padlock in the fourth."" ""The floor and ceiling in all the rooms were made of boards, well planed"""" The next inventory of the estate dates back to 1789. Judging by the description of the house, there were no changes in its planning structure. However, it contains very important information. Thus, when describing the last living room, the inscription in Polish ”Roku Tysiąc Siedemset Dwadziestego Czwartego"" is mentioned on the support beam. This dating may indicate that in 1724 the building was built or substantially rebuilt. In addition to the above - mentioned inventory , the Lviv Scientific Library named after V. Stefanik has a watercolor by Yu . peshka of the early 19th century . (no later than 1810), on which the entire estate is represented. The center of the composition was the described wooden house. It was rectangular in plan and covered with a high hip roof. Not far from the house there are one-storey buildings of an economic complex. In the foreground there is a tavern and a mill on the stave, then a chapel behind the stave. In the 19th century. the estate has been reconstructed. Exact information about the time of perestroika has not been found in written sources, but, most likely, according to researchers V. Denisov, V. Kukuni, the reconstruction was carried out by Evstafy Ivanovich Prushinsky in the early 1880s, no later than 1883 A. T. Fedoruk attributes the reconstruction of the estate to 1890-1895. The estate was surrounded by a metal wrought-iron fence. A well-maintained park, a new front entrance to the manor house was made along a wide linden alley from the north-west side. The layout of the park has lost its regularity, but its general features have not changed. Landscape compositions were formed in place of the baskets. A manor house, an outbuilding, was built, more precisely, rebuilt, old outbuildings were demolished, a new economic yard was created, and an industrial complex appeared on the site of the old one. As a result of the reconstruction, the manor house received an asymmetric three-dimensional copposition. To the north-eastern facade of an old wooden house of the early 18th century. a stone two-storey volume was added. The new stone volume was covered with a four-pitched roof with a cornice of considerable removal. The risalits under the gable roofs are completed with triangular pediments decorated with invalid half-timbered windows. The reconstruction of the old part of the building was carried out extremely organically. Wooden carved details are widely used in the architectural design of facades: window frames, pediments, listening windows. The main entrance is highlighted by an original portico, the visor of which was supported by carved wooden columns on a high plinth."        </item>
        <item>"The modern Gorky Central Children\'s Park in Minsk is a monument of history, architecture and landscape art. The territory occupied by the park was first marked on the plan of Minsk in 1801. A large plot adjacent to the river with the inscription ”City Garden"" was allocated on the eastern outskirts of the city. The second design plan of the city of the beginning of the XIX century shows the layout of the park. It was divided into two parts by the Svisloch River. The main part of the park was located on the right bank. On both sides, its territory was bounded by streets named Zakharyevskaya and Policyskaya (modern pr. Independence and Ya. Kupala Street). It was planned to dig a small channel around an artificial island, build a bridge over the Svisloch and thus connect the right-bank and left-bank parts of the park, lay several alleys that diverged from the bridge in different directions. The grand opening of the new park took place on May 1 , 1805 . This event was described in some detail in his memoirs by the Polish actor and director K. Skibinsky: “On May 1, the grand opening of the park, founded by His Excellency Korneev, the interim governor, took place. On that day, the city organized a magnificent evening with a military orchestra and artists under the glow of illuminations and with banners. We were all in black tailcoats, ladies in white dresses with bouquets were performing a solemn cantata. In the end, the evening ended with a magnificent fireworks display. And now this garden is kept in perfect order"" the city plans of 1809 and 1810, as well as the memoirs of contemporaries, show how the Minsk City Park looked in the first years of its existence. V. Bronevsky, who visited Minsk in 1810, described the park as follows: ”The public Garden, as something rare, unprecedented in this side, pleased me more than the city itself; I came to it four times and always walked with equal pleasure... The Minsk Garden owes its existence to the former Governor Korneev, who left a good memory for himself with many useful institutions; all citizens treat him with praise. The location of the garden on the plain on both sides of the river, does honor to the knowledge and taste of His Excellency. I have seen a lot of gardens, and in comparison I put the local one among the best; it will be excellent when the trees grow and all the work started according to the plan is over. The art of the glorious Lenotre is already outdated - they are beginning to expel it from newly erected gardens; and indeed, there is nothing more uniform and therefore more boring than its straight avenues, cropped alleys dissected into triangles, parallelograms and other symmetrical figures… The Minsk Garden is located on the models of English gardens; only in decent places the best is borrowed from Lenotr, who has disgraced nature everywhere in his annoying way. Mr. Korneev did not allow the scissors to touch a single tree, and they grow luxuriantly in all their glory."" Then there is a detailed description of the layout of the park and the main structures on its territory: “Three straight wide avenues, killed by sand, go one to the river, another to the right of this along its bank, and the third to the left of the second leads to a huge pavilion placed on beautiful columns. Channels are dug from the river in both directions, which Indus go in a straight line, the Indus form a streamlet flowing around a small island, the Indus flow into a regular basin. The side curves of the road intersect the main vistas and the river in all directions so that the garden together makes up a maze in which Theseus does not need Ariadne\'s thread, because a Chinese figured, or the simplest rustic trestle bridge, or a grotto, or a bathhouse, or a fragile stump, a ruin or some other decoration will show the real road. In the middle of the garden there is a pyramidal obelisk, on one side of which is written: ""To the nobility and citizenship after the labors of rest."" In front of the pavilion, large gazebos and a gallery for dancing, there are regular flowers, around which fragrant and other shrubs are surrounded by crowns and garlands; in short, there are many ideas in the garden, but they are all in place and built according to perfectly accepted and beautiful drawings."" In 1817, the next Minsk layout project was approved, according to which the city was built for 40 years. According to this plan, a significant reconstruction of the city park was also planned (on the plan it is designated under No. 27 as the “City Garden”). First of all, a gradual expansion of the park\'s territory in the eastern direction was envisaged. An analysis of the later plans of the city showed that the project proposals laid down in the master plan for the development of Minsk were never implemented. A large orchard has been preserved to the east of the park, and hay fields that were rented out adjoined the river. The park is presented in some detail on the 1839 plan. The main park alleys and structures are indicated here: a monument in honor of the opening of the garden, a Jordan, gazebos, a swimming pool, swings, flower beds, bridges. Since the 30s of the XIX century. among the documents of the Minsk City Duma and the city Council are materials on the ongoing repair work in the city park. For example, in 1836, the Minsk governor addressed the city authorities with a letter indicating the need to repair 8 bridges, 3 gazebos, a gatehouse and a fence with gates in the park. The estimate for all the works was compiled by the Minsk provincial architect M. Hrshchanovich. It follows from the report on the completed works that the following was done: 3 gazebos were repaired, 8 bridges were repaired, their railings were painted, the roof was covered and painted on the gatehouse, the musical balcony was redone and painted, two new bridges made of birch wood “without bark cleaning” were made, stairs, doors, windows, floor were repaired in the bathhouse, the picket fence around the garden was repaired, and in some places it was replaced with a new one, the benches were painted. In 1839-1841, work was carried out on the improvement of the city garden. In the spring of 1840, the park suffered from flooding. Soon, work began to eliminate the losses caused. They mainly concerned the repair of bridges and fencing. At the same time, the idea arose to make a live fence-from willow trees, tallow, broom, etc. The next repair of the fence was carried out in 1849. Architect K. Khrshchanovich prepared an estimate for the restoration of the fence and bridges, as well as for the construction of a new gazebo. What the park looked like in the middle of the 19th century., the testimonies of contemporaries have been preserved. To quote an excerpt from the book of P. M. Shpilevsky\'s ""Journey through Polesie and the Belarusian region"": ""in addition to the description of the New Place, I consider it necessary to talk about the city, or, as some Minsk residents call it, the governor\'s garden. This garden owes its origin to the once former, at the very end of the last century and at the beginning of the present, Minsk civil governor Korneev, in whose honor and the memory of his merits in the place of the garden where, they say, he planted the first tree himself, a monument was erected – a cone-shaped column with (inscription: ""this garden is planted and divorced by the diligence and diligence of the Minsk governor Korneev."" The most prominent place for the garden was chosen, on the bank of the Svisloch River, on the mountain. Starting in May, the garden is filled every year with almost the whole city: in the evenings music plays in it, on high-quality days there is illumination and sometimes fireworks. In front of the garden there is a birch grove, separated from the center by a Svisloch, encircling the rest of the garden, and when connected to a small channel on the left side, forming a rather beautiful peninsula. The birch grove is so dense that it almost never lets the sun\'s rays through the thicket of its greenery. It is all dotted with paths, paths and alleys adjacent to the Svisloch, on the banks of which on the right side there is a house built by A.V. Semenov, where he lived in the summer; near this house there is a small artificial hill, called Ustinya for some unknown reason, connected by means of a small bridge on a small groove with a Mound cut by spiral paths bordered with flowers. To the left of the groove beats a small spring (krinitsa) with iron waters, surrounded by a round well. Behind the bridge there are several small front gardens, behind which a rather beautiful bridge with benches has already been thrown across the Svisloch. Behind the bridge, your eye can see a number of several roadways and alleys leading in different directions through the bridges, then to the walnut, then to the lime, then to the poplar, then to the spruce or chestnut alley. The best view of alleys and groves opens directly from the bridge, and especially on the right side of it. A very wide alley runs straight ahead, shaded on both sides by shady elms, linden trees, maples, chestnuts, and rests against the back fence of the garden: at the corner of the alley there are wooden stages for musicians. To her right, a shady, dark, large alley of evergreen firs stretches in a semicircle – an alley washed by the waters of the Svisloch and embracing the garden along the river almost to its very end. To the left of the fir alley is a luxurious young poplar grove, in the depths of which there is a wooden pavilion. A small stream of Svisloch flows near the pavilion, in the middle of which a crystal-clear spring with sulfuric waters breaks through from under the root of an alder tree, which has brought considerable relief to more than one scrofulous person. Many of the locals and even visitors come here in the morning and drink several glasses of water on an empty stomach; this water has the property of laxative, but not relaxing; raw gives off a strong smell of sulfur, and boiled is very suitable for tea. It\'s just a pity that the source does not have a decent fence."" At the end of the 1850s, an essay of vl. Syrocomly” Minsk"", dedicated to the history of the city. In the section “a cursory overview of the current state of Minsk”, the author also noted the City Garden: “...let\'s complete our essay with a list of the most important parks. Naturally, the first place is occupied here by the Governor\'s Park, named after its founder, Governor Zakhar Korneev. The park was founded around 1800."        </item>

    </string-array>
</resources>